Okay. Okay. Um, good morning. Welcome
back. Um, any outstanding issues from
yesterday or any questions you have so
far?
Anyone?
>> Okay. Sure.
I was pondering the issue of um why
don't we confront our um anger
these types of emotions directly and
head on.
>> Um reminded that um sometimes we need to
go all the way down to be able to get
back up.
>> Um and to myself at least and this is
particularly personal. Um, I think part
of going to Inferno is also to see kind
of the full length and consequence of
all these um emotions because just like
the mirrored flame you talked about
yesterday, sometimes when you have a
negative emotional reaction to
something, it's because there's
something in you that reacts to that.
And so I think sometimes you don't go
tackle some problem head on, but you
need to kind of dive deep into it really
really deep in order to emerge from the
other side.
>> That's right. Thank you so much. Yeah.
Uh yes.
>> Um so the whole journey into helping
these beings like is it reasonable to
assume that Dr. writer was inspired by
the being
to help his lover
extremely.
>> Yeah. Exactly. Yes. Thank you. Yes.
Exactly. So Dante is trying to create a
renaissance, right? He's trying to
um delve deep into the memory of western
civilization into human civilization and
recall all these great traditions that
have been lost over time. not only
Orpheus but also Dionius um basically
the great legends of the Greek tradition
and again most of most of these things
are are lost but even though the memory
has been lost the feeling is still there
right so he's trying to conjure up these
this nostalgia exactly yes ortheus is
very important uh for for Dante okay um
any more comments okay so um with
regards to yesterday I want to make two
clarifications
So yesterday I was asked a question. Um
I said that Mary's child um if she had a
child before Jesus and if this child
were to die uh as an infant then this
child would be next to God. And I want
to explain my logic here. Uh because
what Dante's trying to convey and this
is a really important thing you must
understand about Dante is he's saying
that God's justice is perfect. Meaning
that with enough love and with enough
imagination, you can reason out the
logic of everything that God does, it'll
be convincing and understandable to
everyone around you. Okay. And so the
logic is this.
Um Mary is the queen of heaven. And
she's the queen of heaven because she is
the best of us. Okay. She is she is the
person who is able to give birth to uh a
god Jesus.
And she is so perfect. We have to assume
that her mother is perfect as well or
her mother is also very virtuous. That's
why Anna the mother is also
um in heaven and in the uh highest
sphere next next to God. So if we just
work out the logic, if um Anna is
uh virtuous, the the most virtuous,
which allows for Mary to be even more
virtuous, the perfect in virtue, then
we're going to assume that whatever
child uh Mary has will also be extremely
virtuous given the fact that uh she uh
the child is born of Mary, but also
given the fact that Mary is will parent
this child, right? And now so um it is
entirely possible for the child to screw
this up and you know just become an
adult and just do a lot of bad things.
That's possible but if the child dies as
an infant then you have to assume that
this child will be a virtuous person as
well and will deserve a seat next to
God. Uh you have to make that assumption
according to to this logic. So if the
child dies at um as an infant then God
in his infinite wisdom in his perfect
justice will assign this infant a seat
next to him. Okay, does that make sense?
Logically again everything has to be
explained um logically and you can
actually reason this out. All right. Um
this is important because uh yeah go
ahead.
>> No but but u this is regarding to the
unborn child, right? um prematurely
dying before uh they are able to reason.
I feel like Dante bringing this up
towards the end as we reach the kind of
like the pinnacle uh of heaven.
>> This is the pinnacle of heaven.
>> Yeah. As as we are in the pinnacle of
heaven, I think Dante is I I I wouldn't
call it humility, but Dante is admitting
that there are unknown unknowns
primarily around the question of free
will.
>> Mh. Because free will consciousness
until today it's not a figured out
subject right and and and free will as
we we talked about u with regard to God
God is trying to God gives us free will
but God probably doesn't even wasn't the
one who created free will that means
free will transcend it might be
something beyond I don't know it's
further
>> beyond the beyond god reasoning even
right
>> because because if If you're trying to
generate something like like we've
discussed, God wants to um it's probably
not something that you can create on
your own,
>> right?
>> It's like energy, right? Right. The
reason why we we we we mind energy that
we need energy is because it's not
something that we can kind of come up
from scratch,
>> right? Okay. Yeah. So, um I I think uh
where I agree is like um there are no
absolutes in the universe. Okay. There
are a lot of things that are special
cases and in these special cases
um you have to really use your love and
imagination to figure these special
cases out. Okay, in the infant case is
again the hardest theological problem in
the universe. Okay, so this is to
address the issue why would Mary's child
be granted access to the imperium. Okay.
The other issue that we that we
discussed um last class is
um why would Virgil agree to being
Dante's guide? And I was a bit being in
tongue and cheek. I said, "Well, it's
because PH is really hot." Um and
there's some truth to that, but it's not
it's never that complicated. It's never
that simple, right? Because if you
actually read the passage, um what Peter
said to Virgil is that if you were to do
this, then God will reward you. God
knows about this. We have a special um
permission from God to help Dante, even
though he's still not dead, ascend to to
heaven. You will guide him from hell to
purgatory, and then I'll pick him up
pick him up in purgatory, and then I
will take him to heaven. Okay? And so,
um, Virgil has opportunity to enter
paradise, but we know for a fact he
doesn't. He's not in paradise. So, this
creates a question for us. How is it
that Virgil is granted access to
paradise? Because all he has to do is
guide Dante. Okay, we know that Dante is
a access paradise. So, Virgil succeeds
in his mission. And we know that God has
already made Virgil this promise. You
helped Dante reach paradise and you went
to paradise as well. But
Virgil is not in paradise.
So this creates a mystery for us. Okay?
and and and and that's why I wanted to
read read it in this order because you
recognize you you because you recognize
that there must be something about
Virgil, okay, that does not allow him to
access paradise. So why couldn't he
access paradise given the logic of of of
this class so far? Yes.
>> So this is something I've been curious
since the first day, but since you
talked about Virgin not being able to
access paradise, this kind of brought
this up to me. So, uh, God is love, God
is light, and you are a measly teacup.
Is it possible for the teacup, it's it's
like the sun, okay? It's like the sun,
like the sun's rays nourish us and help
us, but too much time out in the sun and
we start to blister and we start to get
sunburn. Is it possible for some people
knowing the nature of angels to
purposefully to voluntarily turn away
from God to live in the shade?
Um so look um the answer to the question
why did Virgil not into paradise the
answer is he did not want to he chose
not to go to paradise he chose to stay
in hell and there's something really
important to appreciate if you are to
understand uh the ultimate message of
the divine comedy okay all right so um
let me provide some background before we
we start so
the thing that
Dante
and Virgil both understand is that
poetry is what gives birth to
civilization. Okay? Poetry is what
teaches people how to think, how to
feel, and how to imagine. Without
poetry, there can be no civilization.
And the classic example of this is
Homer.
So, Homer, which we will not read. Um,
and by the way, this is something really
important for you guys to appreciate.
Dante did not read Homer. He did not
have access to the Iliad in the Odyssey
because in this world they spoke Latin
and Homer is written in Greek. Okay? So,
he couldn't actually read Homer and it
was very hard to access a Homer
manuscript at this time. But Homer wrote
the Iliad
and the Odyssey
and
um this will give rise to probably the
greatest civilization in human history,
the Greek civilization. Okay, Athens.
Uh in classical Athens from about uh 450
to 350 B.CE will basically create the
framework for western civilization. This
is a time of Socrates, Plato, Aristotle,
Fusidities, Heroditus, basically
everyone. Okay. Um, and a lot of things
that uh were taught back then, we still
teach. If you go to B, if if if you go
back to biology class back at this time,
it would not be that different from
biology class today. Okay, it's pretty
um amazing to think about. What then
will happen is that Alexander
the great will then conquer the world.
Okay, basically Persia which was most of
the world at this time and he will take
Greek civilization as far as uh India.
Now, Exon the Great is interesting
because he's really the first great
world conqueror in history and um
there's a lot of debate as to how
Alexander was able to accomplish this
but the main reason is and I I know this
is hard for you guys to appreciate but
no one uh no one before him wanted to do
this. Okay, let's think about this
logically. Before war was about
extortion, right? either you give me
land or you give me money or you give me
you know hostages or I will come and
invade you. So it's bas basically an
extortion racket. So when Alexander was
threatening Persia basically the person
said to him we'll give you half the
empire okay like half the empire which
is a lot of land we'll give you like a
trillion dollars but don't invade us.
And usually this was enough to
buy peace, right?
But Alexander was like, "I don't want
your money. I don't want your land. I
don't even want your throne. I want
glory."
And again before nobody who was king,
nobody had an army would think like this
because you have an army to feed. They
want woman. They want land. They want
riches. And so we have to appease your
army. Right? Like no all I want is
glory. I want to be remembered forever
as the world's greatest conqueror. So I
don't I don't want any of this. And so
you're like, where where did where did
he get this idea? And the answer is the
Iliad, Homer, Achilles, right? If you
read the Iliad,
um Achilles is very clear. He's like,
I'm in the beach of Troy. I know I will
die here in a couple years. I know that
because I was given this prophecy. I
don't care because I was told that by
coming to Troy I will be remembered as
the greatest warrior in human history.
Okay, that's what I want. I want the
glory.
Um and so that's why Alexander did what
he did and this and he was able to bring
Greek civilization as far as India.
Okay. And so what is the basis of Greek
civilization
to understand Greek civilization? You
you do understand two ideas. Okay. These
two ideas are the basis of Greek
civilization. They are erete
and uronia.
Er means excellence. Okay. And the idea
of is
what matters is to stand out from the
crowd. What matters is to demonstrate
your excellence to
um the world. And you can do that by two
ways for you can do that one on a
battlefield by being a great hero in
which people will celebrate you and sing
sing songs about you like Achilles right
mean great war on the battlefield but
another way of doing it is to be a great
speech maker to stand in front of your
peers your colleagues and give a speech
that rouses them to action that
convinces them to do good that sways
them to your opinion okay so these are
two way main ways in which you do that
either through speech making or for war
fighting. Okay, war fighting the
exemplar is Achilles. Speechm, the
exemplar is Odysius. Okay, so these are
the two main ideas undergirling
uh Greek civilization
and
Greek civilization because of these two
ideas is able to become the greatest
civilization in history because
everyone's trying to be the best.
Everyone's trying to be uh to transform
the world. Okay, just as what Dante told
us, right? To live a life of faith, hope
and love. Well, at this time, they were
trying to live a life of ereete and
udeimmonia. Basically the same thing.
And this is what made Greek civilization
uh so compelling and which which allowed
Greek civilization to spread around the
world. Then what happened of course is
the rise of Rome. And the Romans were
different. The Romans became the
greatest empire
in the world because they focused only
on war. All they cared about was
defeating their enemies. They were able
do to do that because of the focus on
the idea of piety,
loyalty,
obedience to the fathers, to the
senators, the uh to the history of Rome
and to the gods. Okay. So this is a very
different conception of uh the world.
And but the problem of course is that
once the Romans encountered Greek
civilization like wow um Greek
civilization is so much more
sophisticated so much more cultured than
our civilization. They knew that because
of homework because they learned Greek,
they read the Iliad, they read read the
site and they and they were like this is
this is what civilization should be
about. This is beautiful. Okay. They
memorized the Iliad in the Odyssey as
part of their education and it became to
act out um Greek civilization. And so
the leaders of Rome at this time, mainly
Augustus Caesar, the emperor, the first
emperor of Rome,
uh they're about the son of Julius
Caesar, he recognized that over time
Roman civilization would be conquered by
Greek civilization. Territorially,
militarily, the Romans have conquered
the Greeks. But over time, culturally,
the Greeks will conquer the Romans.
Okay? So, what do you do about this?
What you have to do is
confront Homer directly. Okay? You need
a new poet. You need a new epic poem in
order to replace
Homer. And that of course is Virgil's
Iniad.
Okay? So, Augustus Caesar sponsored
Virgil's writing of the Iniad. In fact,
they wrote it together. Okay? Because
whenever Virgil finished a particular
part, he went to Augusta Caesar and
August, I think you should do this. I
think you should do that. Okay. But but
it was a co-quad
together because we have to in order to
fully appreciate uh Dante. And so with
the Iniad, with Homer, uh love
was at the center of civilization. Okay.
Now with Rome,
um it is piety or obedience that gives
rise to civilization. Obedience is the
main organizing principle of
civilization. And this becomes the
framework also for
uh the Catholic Church, right? Uh Paul
and Augustine will work together across
centuries to create the fe theoretical
framework for the Catholic Church. And
basically you create obedience by
instilling fear in people. And so Europe
descends into the dark ages because fear
becomes the main emotion at this time.
Okay. People are focused on not doing
anything wrong so they can go to heaven.
Right? That limits their creativity.
And Dante recognizes this. And so what
he's going to do is even without having
read Homer, okay, he is going to
resurrect Homer and create the divine
comedy.
Okay. But the challenge for Dante is
much more greater than for Homer. Homer
could come and at this time this is the
Greek dark ages. There's really no
central authority. They would like a lot
of the civilization was destroyed in the
Bronze Age collapse. So it's a blank
slate. Okay. So he could come and he
could recite his poetry and people would
be inspired by it. He had no opposition.
Dante is different. Dante has to fight
an empire which have a church as well as
a god which is Virgil. Okay. So um
what you want to do uh ideally is
basically construct your cosmology.
Okay, which is paradise, right? We we've
already read
um Dante cosmology in paradise. We now
know exactly what he thinks. Then what
you need to do is go convince people,
right? You convince you, you engage in
debate
and then you hopefully uh spread.
Okay. The problem of course is you can't
do that at the time history. The
Catholic Church is the do is dominant.
So you can't actually spread what you
believe. You can't actually debate
people. Okay. So the divine comedy has
been constructed in a way uh so that
Donn can spread his cosmology but in a
way that people don't know he's doing it
and in a way that convinces people. All
right. So what he has to do is basically
agree with Virgil, make Virgil
the hero of Divine Comedy, then he has
to subvert Virgil,
okay? Or maybe subversion, show to us
that maybe Virgil is not God, maybe he's
fallible, maybe he's just wrong. And
then that will then allow him to now
promote his cosmology. Okay?
um it's cosmology and that's why divine
comedy is constructed in the way that it
is. He starts off with hell which
celebrates Virgil. He goes to purgatory
in which a lot of ideas of Virgil are
being subverted and then now we can
ascend to paradise
um which then allows Don to reveal to
all of us his cosmology. Okay, does that
make sense? Okay, now it sounds very
simple, but you actually do this in
practice. You you can appreciate how
hard it is to do, right? Because ideally
you want to first create your cosmology,
then figure out how to convince other
people. But Dante has to start the other
way around. Okay? Meaning in his mind,
he already needs to figure out the
entire
cosmos before he writes anything down.
Okay? Okay. And that's what he that's
what he does. So,
um, having read the Divine Comedy, I can
tell you that it's a Divine Comedy that
convinced me there must be a God. Before
I read the Divine Comedy four years ago,
I was an atheist. I was utterly
convinced the world, the universe is
emergent. It's materialistic. It's all
random. There is no God. There can't be
a God. But having study, it is
impossible for me to explain how Dante
was able to do this if he did not have
divine inspiration, if he was not guided
by the Holy Spirit. Okay? If there was
not the universe showing him the path
because not only you have to construct
this way, but you have you have to
maintain consistency throughout the
process. meaning you have to like drop
basically Easter eggs from the very
beginning showing that Virgil is
compromised. Okay. Otherwise, it won't
work that way. All right. Yes.
>> Um I agree that the Divine Comedy is a
great work. However, I don't think it's
a divine work. Like I don't think its
existence proves the existence of God
because this is what a world builder
does. The Easter eggs and the structure
you're talking about, this is very
similar to what modern world builders
do. They establish a framework first and
then they write about their world. So if
you're saying that this is a great book,
I agree. But if you're saying that it
proves the existence of God, not so
much.
>> Okay. So um okay, that's about
criticism. Okay. So two points. First of
all, Donnie did not call his work divine
comedy. He called
not divine. Divine came later. Why why
would all these great poets
want to add divine toad?
Okay. So if you talk to someone like TS
Elliott, if you talk to any great poet
of the 20th century, they will tell you
there are two great poets in human
history. They are Homer and they are
Dante. Maybe some will say Shakespeare,
maybe some include Milton, but they all
agree there are two great poets of human
history. They are Homer and they are um
Dante. And the vine was added later on.
Okay, remember at this time in history,
you can't call anything divine because
it's heresy, right? the Catholic Church
is going to chop off your head. How dare
you say something's divine? Only the
Catholic Church has the authority to say
what is divine or not. All right? So, it
was not called divine at the time. It
was added on later. That's point um
number one. Point number two is that
what's interesting is that if you talk
to scholars
um there's widespread disagreement about
the construction of these great poems.
So for example, Homer um for the reason
there are many scholars who do not
believe that Homer was a real person.
They thought that Homer was a collection
of individuals very much like the movie
making process where you might have a
director but you also have a
cinematographer, you have an editor, uh
you have a collection of individuals.
Okay. Some some even argue that the
Iliad and the Odyssey were not written
by the same person.
uh Emily Wilson who um translated both
idiat in the Odyssey. If you go to Yale
today director studies the translation
you actually read of Homer is is
translated by Emily Wilson but I read
her preface to the Odyssey. When I teach
Odyssey I actually use Emily Wilson and
she said that well I personally think
that Homer was not a one person. It was
a committee. It was and it was very much
a collective process. And I mean
I'm sort of surprised by this because if
you look at any great work of art, it's
always an individual genius at work.
Okay? There's never an example of a
great painting or a great piece of music
or a great piece of literature where
it's a collective effort where two two
individuals are working together. It
only leads to chaos. Okay? That's let me
finish please. Okay.
>> The Bible.
>> The Bible is a great work of religion.
But if you read the Bible, okay, you
will know that it's complete under
chaos. There are certain parts of the
Bible, for example, Genesis, which is
great literature. And we all agree that
a lot of the Bible was written by a
person called the Yahweh is Jay. Okay?
If you just go spend some time and look
at the scholarship on the Bible, okay,
they they all tell you the Genesis was
written by at least four people. All
right, and the story of Adam and Eve was
written by one person, only one person
who is a Yahwehist. And if you if you
read um Hero Bloom, the book of Jay, he
makes the argument that the that that
Jay was a poet. She was not a it was a
she. She was not a priest. She was not a
uh theologian. she was a poet. Okay. So,
whatever part of the Bible which is
extremely poetic, this includes Genesis,
it also includes um the book of the
Gospel of Mark, it was written by a
poet. Okay. And if you actually do
literary analysis, you can actually see
the spark of poetry in certain aspects
of the Bible. Yes.
>> I'm I'm just going along with the
hypothesis that okay, say Dante has a
framework, right? Dante is a world
builder. What ex I don't know. I'm not
scholarred in this. So I like what is
what exactly is Dante's framework is my
question. Right? If if if if assume with
the hypothesis that Dante started up
with the framework, what exactly is the
framework? Is it mathematical in nature?
Is it scientific? It's experimental.
What is it?
>> Okay. All right. So let's let's go back
to uh Homer. Okay. Homer has had to be a
real person. And the reason why is if
you actually read the Iliad in the
Odyssey, and I suggest you do because
they're both tremendously beautiful
works of literature.
The people inside it are real people,
okay? They are real people that and you
could feel as though you could meet them
in real life and have a conversation
with Achilles and have a conversation
with this and everyone else in
uh in it. And the same thing with the
line comedy where you can actually like
meet Beatatrice and she's a consistent
real person. You can meet Dante, you can
meet Virgil and they're all consistent
people with real psychology. Okay. And
he'll bloom again. The criteria he uses
in order to judge the authenticity of
character is does this person hear
himself or herself talk? Meaning is this
person capable of self-reflection?
Okay. An example of this is where Virgil
is telling uh Dante, so Beatatrice
promised me access to heaven if I help
you. And then and then he hears himself
says, "Wait a minute, but that seems
like I'm selfish. That's that makes me
seem very egotistical." So then he
changes and says, "Oh, but I didn't care
because I was so enraptured by her
beauty that I agreed anyway." Okay. So
that's what happens when you can when
the character can hear himself talk
right line I say this but oops I see the
effect on that person so I'm I'm going
to make changes to it and if you read um
Homer and Dante that happens with
characters all the time when during the
speech process the person also step be
disassociating and and analyzing his or
her own speech okay and that's what
makes it authentic and that's why it had
to be written by one person only because
only an individual is capable of doing
that. Okay. Does that make sense? All
right. Okay. So, let us um continue.
Um
oh, we're now candle three. Okay.
And again, something the reason why I
want to read paradise first is I want to
show you that um this world is complete.
These are real uh people. And even in
Inferno, we can see foreshadowings of
Paradise. We can only see how Donnie
subverting Virgil as an authority. And
he has to subvert Virgil in order to uh
promote his ideas. Okay.
>> Through me the way into the suffering
city. Through me the way to the eternal
pain. Through me the way that runs among
the lost. Justice urged on my high
artifificer.
My maker was divine authority. The
highest wisdom and the primal love.
Before me nothing but eternal things
were made. And I endure eternally.
Abandon every hope who enter here.
>> Okay. So this is a very famous um sign
to warning to people who who enter hell.
Okay. So if you want to come to hell,
abandon every hope
uh who enter here. Okay. Uh let's keep
on going.
>> Verse 10. These words, their aspect was
obscure.
I read inscribed above a gateway. And I
said, "Master, their meaning is
difficult for me." And he to me as one
who comprehends here one must leave
behind all hesitation. Here every
cowardice must meet its death. For we
have reached the place of which I spoke
where you will see the miserable
miserable people, those who have lost
the good of the intellect. And when with
gladness in his face, he placed his hand
upon my own to comfort me he drew me in
among the hidden things. Here sigh and
lamentations and loud cries were echoing
across the starless air. So that as soon
as I set out, I wept.
>> Wait, stop. Okay, right. Abandon every
hope here. Okay. Turn to hell. You must
abandon hope. What
does Dante mean by hope?
>> The hope that he one day he can see
Beatrice again.
>> No, no. I'm saying more generally what
how's hope defined by Dante? Yes.
But what is arrogance?
The ego. Yes. Okay. Yes. Did
>> you hope of getting out of it?
>> Yeah. Just the ego. Okay. Abandon your
sense of self. Abandon
every a sense of agency and autonomy
that you have. Okay. That's what allows
you to enter hell. You understand?
Okay. Abandon hope. Abandon your ego.
>> Yes. Hope would also conotate a
a relation to time. You hope for the
future. You don't hope for and so this
is still beyond time and space that you
spoken about earlier.
>> Yes. Yes. Right. Okay. Does that make
sense? Okay. But this is so this is
extremely
um provocative idea where you're taught
like your ego is what leads you to hell,
right? your lust, your desire, that's
what leads you to hell. But we know from
paradise
that Dante defines hope as arrogance.
So abandon your arrogance. Those who
enter here,
right? Abandon your belief that you by
yourself
can escape hell, can redeem yourself
from hell, then you can be here. Okay?
Does that make sense?
>> Yes.
>> I wonder who wrote these words. Was it
like Virgil the writer or was it um
sorry, was it Dante the writer or was it
Virgil or was it like a classical
inscription written by like Homer or
Virgil?
>> Uh mo mo most of this will be Dante.
Okay. And where it is someone else Dante
will reference.
Okay. Because again, Don is a very
arrogant person. He wants you to
recognize the originality
of his poem, right? Okay. So, this is
Dante. And again, the idea of hope is
consistent, right? We know from heaven
that hope is arrogance, the assertion of
self, the belief that you can change the
world for the better. And what Don is
saying here is like if you want to enter
hell,
you have to believe
you have no agency. You have no control
over anything. That's a pre
preconditioning precondition for
entering hell. Okay. Does it make sense?
Yes.
>> I would like to highlight that it's it's
actually on the person to decide whether
he wants to enter, right? It's this is
sending a message to the person who is
entering hell.
>> That's right. Okay. Do you understand?
If you in your heart don't believe you
should be here, if you in your heart
believe you can still escape hell, you
can do so because the fundamental law of
the universe is free will. Yes. Yeah. A
little bit confused because in the hell
just like you said, Danty just gave up,
right? He's his hope. But uh there's
still some somebody who just stealing
the house just like uh Caesar or some
kind of emperor you know even the the
the the godfather.
Do you think that they were all just uh
give up their their hope? No. Well,
look, I'm not trying to make a
theological argument, okay? I'm just
trying to say what Dante's idea is for
Dante. Everyone in hell is there because
he or she chooses to be there. He
chooses to be there because he or she
has given up
his or her free will. Does it make
sense? Okay.
It's a choice you make. Whether it be in
heaven or hell, it's a choice you make.
Okay. Uh let's let's let's keep on
going.
Verse
25.
Strange utterances, horrible
pronouncements, accents of anger, words
of suffering, and voices shrill and
faint and beating hands all went to make
a tumult that would whirl forever
through that turbid timeless air like
sand that eddies when a whirlwind
swirls.
And I my head oppressed by horror said,
"Master, what is it that I hear? Who are
those people so defeated by their pain?"
And he to me,
>> okay, so so defeated by their pain.
Okay, it's the the construction of the
words signifies
these people
have
given up. You understand? Defeated by
their pain.
These are defeated people, right? And
this goes against
what we understand about people in hell
who are people who just do tremendous
evil.
Okay, does that make sense? There's a
clear difference.
Okay, let let's keep on going.
Verse 34.
And he to me this miserable way is taken
by the sorry souls of those who lived
without disgrace and without praise.
They now com they now coingle with the
coward angels the company of those who
were not rebels nor faithful to their
god but stood apart
the heavens that their beauty not be
less than have cast them out nor will
deep hell receive them even the wicked
cannot glory in them and I what is it
master that oppresses these souls
compelling them to whail so loud he
answered I shall tell you in few words
those who are here can place no hope in
death and their blind life is so abject
that they are envious of every other
fate. The world will let no fame of
theirs endure. Both justice and
compassion must disdain them. Let us not
talk of them but look and pass. And I
looking more closely saw a banner that
as it wheeled about raised on so quick
that any respit seemed unsuited to it.
Okay. So again all these three different
realms whether they are hell or
purgatory or paradise they all parallel
each other in structure. Okay. So in
paradise it is Beatatrice who is
communicating with Dante teaching Dante.
Here in hell it is Virgil that is
teaching Dante. Can someone explain to
me the difference the difference in the
way that Beatric teaches and the
differences in the way that uh Virgil
teaches? Do you do do you see do you
spot the difference?
>> Yes.
>> Uh maybe because ego because Petra just
do not want the Dy to give up the the
ego but uh yeah the will who just want
him to give up.
>> I guess
seems that uh Petrus inspired more
imagination from Dante whereas Virg just
answers his questions very directly.
>> Exactly. You understand? Yes. Okay. The
major difference is this. Beatric is
trying to be a teacher. As a teacher,
you have to ask questions to your
student. You have to welcome questions.
You have to help provide clue give
provide clues that inspires a student to
come up with his or her own conclusions.
Okay? Virgil is just like this is the
answer. Memorize it. You understand?
It's a very stark difference. Okay.
Virgil has Yes. I'm reminded of
something that another professor of mine
once said. The worst game to play in the
world is guess what the professor is
thinking.
Okay. Okay. All right. Look. All right.
So, do you guys understand the
difference? Okay. Beatrice is trying to
guide ver Dante into self-standing which
helps us
um develop our own self-standing. Virgil
is just trying to explain the rules of
the universe. And for Virgil, these
rules are absolute. So you just must
remember these rules. Okay? Virgil has a
very clear
u explanation for everything. And uh
Dante just must remember this. Okay? And
and this is this is a pattern. This is
how Virgil will talk to uh Dante. And it
mirrors how people are taught at this
stage in history. It mirrors how people
relate to the INIAD. Okay? Because if
you read the Iniad, it's different from
the line comedy, it's different from
Homer in that if you read the line
comedy, it leads it leads you to ask a
lot of question. It inspires you in
action. Whereas uh the Iniad is just
like just obedience, passive acceptance.
Okay? It inspires you to to basically
just sit down and obey. Okay, so that's
the attitude of Virgil. Okay, let's
let's keep on going.
>> Verse 55.
Behind that banner trailed so long a
file of people. I should never have
believed that death could have been made
so many souls. After I had identified a
few, I saw and recognized the shade of
him who made through cowardice the great
refusal. At once I understood with
certainty this company contained the
cowardly, hateful to God and to his
enemies. These wretched ones who never
were alive went naked and were stung
again, again by horse flies and by wasps
that circled them. The insects dre their
faces with their blood which mingled
with their tears fell at their feet
where it was gathered up by sickening
worms. And then looking beyond them, I
could see a crowd along the bank of a
great river at which I said, "Allow me
now to know who are these people,
master, and what law has made them seem
so eager for the crossing, as I can see,
despite the feeble light."
>> Okay, so here in hell, um these people,
these souls are lining up to cross into
uh the inferno. Okay, they have to cross
the river sticks first. And
um while they're waiting, they're being
stung by these insects.
And so what's their response? What are
they doing? First of all, if you were in
camping
and you're being stung by mosquitoes,
right, there are all these insects
around you. What would you do?
Yeah, you would do something about it,
right? You do bug spray or you you start
squatting them, right? What are they
doing about it?
don't know well they are just talking
about they're crying about it
>> you understand okay so it's this passive
acceptance
abandon hope right I cannot alter my
fate
right so that's what hell is hell is
just positivity compliance obedience
acceptance that's what hell is all right
and not only that But Dante
uses a word you do not you would not
expect from these people. Okay. Line 74.
What is this word? What is what? Like
you would not expect this word in hell.
Yeah. Eager, right? You're like what?
People are eager to enter hell.
Okay, let's keep on going.
Uh verse 76.
And he to me when we have stopped along
the melancholy shore of Aaron, then all
these matters will be plain to you. At
that with eyes ashamed, downcast, and
fearing that what I said had given him
offense, I did not speak until we
reached the river. So, how is the
relationship between
uh
Virgil and Dante different from the
relationship between Beatrice and Dante?
Yeah.
>> To Dante. Um Virgil's just a guy to um
um uh and Beatatrice is like um Dante's
uh true love.
>> Yes.
I think for Wirjo he's also like less
patient because he is like given a task
and then he just wanted to complete his
task as quickly as possible but
Beatatric is more like oh I love this
guy so I want to like teach him and make
him better. So there's like a
difference.
>> Yeah. But but I don't think Virgil I I
don't think his motivation is to commit
the task.
What what what's Virgil's problem? Why
is Virgil being impatient?
Why? Why are teachers in your school
where you are, why are they impatient?
>> Yes.
>> Because we're not listening to them in
class.
>> Exactly. Okay. Do you understand?
Because you're you're not
obedient.
Okay. All right. Let's let's keep on
going.
>> Yeah. Yes. Like I think that's mistaking
the symptom for the cause. Like you're
being disobedient so they become
impatient. I think I think there's a
root cause to all this. And I think it's
uh the explanation that we heard before
like it's just a job to
>> um
okay we already establish that Beatrice
promise Virgil access to heaven if he
completes this task, right? We already
know that Virgil will choose not to go
to paradise.
So, so
why do you think
Virgil chooses not to go to paradise?
>> Yes.
>> So, I was wondering about this because
Virgil is
seems to be coming from a a a Roman
multi-
multi-god framework, it seems. So, is
there is there a chance that like Virgil
sees himself in this Roman classical
sense
where he's inside now Dante's Christian
framework and displeased with it
perhaps?
>> Yeah. Yeah. V Virgil. Yes.
>> Maybe Virgil's already abandoned hope.
>> Uh, no he hasn't, right? Because what?
And and how we know he has not abandoned
hope.
>> Uh how about obedience? Because Virgil
just have obedience to to the Rome to
the authority.
>> No. No. Okay. Okay. Let's answer this
question. Okay.
Virgil has not abandoned hope. How do we
know that?
>> Because he was willing to take on this
task.
>> Exactly. You understand that? Okay. If
you have abandoned hope, you don't think
I'm capable of this task. Leave me
alone. Okay. This is a really important
idea to understand. Hope is the
assertion of the ego. Okay. So he is so
he has to have an ego to think that oh I
can lead this guy out of hell. Okay. You
haven't been able to escape hell but
you're able to help this guy escape
hell. That's ego. Okay. So if
Dante sorry if Virgil is out abandoned
hope
right
then what is he doing in hell?
Like go back to the like
teacher analogy. There are some really
good teachers like who could be at a
really good school, they choose to be at
a bad school.
Uh yeah. Yes.
>> Like I said, maybe he chose to be there.
Maybe uh because he came from um a
polytheistic background and I hate to
get into semantics here, but maybe he's
just not willing to accept this
Christian framework of the world. And so
he would rather stay in hell where he
doesn't have to face, you know, the one
God every day.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. So like let's
make this really simple. Okay. You've
all had teachers, right? You've all had
teachers. Some of you are even teachers.
What why do teachers teach differently?
There are some teachers who want you ask
questions, who give you space to
explore, who who want you to make
mistakes. There's some teachers who are
like we have a teaching plan 45 minutes
every minute it's planned already let's
just do it and if we don't if and like
don't ask questions. Okay. What's the
difference between these two teachers?
>> Yes.
>> The amount of imagination they inspire.
>> Okay. Well, the effect is different. But
I'm saying what's motivating these two
these [clears throat] two teachers? Yes.
I think uh one one uh one they genuinely
care about their student and one like
really doesn't.
>> So why why is he teaching that?
>> Yeah. Yes.
>> One is more for like the material drive
like to get a salary and the other is
maybe like on another level where they
actually want to inspire the student.
>> Okay. Um I've worked as a teacher. Okay.
And I can tell you most teachers
I mean like they're not doing a job for
the money because the money sucks. Okay.
I'm not saying all all teachers. I'm
saying like most teachers like the money
the money just sucks. Like Okay. Like I
mean uh yeah. Yeah. Go ahead.
>> As a teacher like the first style is
probably when the student is more
promising and you want this person to go
further like he can figure it out by
himself. So you ask more questions and
sometimes when students are like really
don't have time for that and you have
exam coming and if they're not that
smart then you're like hey here's the
answer remember it so you at least get a
B+ you're never going to get hit at A
anyways that could be a reason but that
the second one could also be more
authoritarian like this is the truth
swallow it just like God gives to
Ezekiel like you know don't make it
wrong just do this is the answer yeah
memorize it go ahead
>> um for my experience experience as a
student. I feel like if the teacher
skill is not that great and they don't
really understand the material that well
and they don't have a strong ability in
the in the the the course like the
material itself, they're afraid of you
asking questions and they're kind of
really bad at improv answering
questions. So, they just skip stick to
the script and what they've prepared.
But if the teacher is very knowledgeable
in their field, then usually they're
more open to discussion.
>> Okay. Yeah. Okay. All right. Any anyone
else? Uh yes.
>> Uh because teacher what they've been
teach is not about themselves. It's
about the authority about school who
want them to teach. So there must be
some teacher who just do their job well
because they just be paid to to teach
you but not just try to uh you know have
willingness to to teach you, you know.
Uh yeah. Yes. At the back.
>> Uh if you're open to questions, your
goal is to transfer the information.
Whereas if you're closed, you just want
to drop the information. Uh and just
like, yeah, I've done my job. I just
drop the info. Whereas asking questions
is more [clears throat] about transfer
and you want your students to have the
most of what you said.
>> Oh, okay. Yeah. I mean, like look, look,
it's very simple. Okay. For those
teachers who allow questions to be
asked, it's coming from a place of love,
right? You want students to learn, but
for for teachers who care about the
results, it's a it's coming from a place
of control. Does that make sense? You
want to be able to control the
situation. And that I think is the
difference between Virgil and Beatrice.
And it'll become much more clear as we
go along where Beatric is coming from a
place of love. She generally wants to
understand and she so she's going to be
patient. They're going to have large
long debates. Whereas for Virgil, he's
coming from a place of control. Okay? He
wants to be able to control how Dante
thinks. He want he wants to be able to
impose
uh his worldview on onto uh Dante. Okay.
So that's why there's this impatient
where you know Dante might ask a
question that um confuses Virgil or
might um create dissonance in in in
Virgil's worldview. So So then Virgil
gets impat
uh Dante senses has a sense of fear.
Okay. Okay. Right. So, so this is going
to be an ongoing dynamic throughout
Inferno. Uh, yes.
>> I just have a question. Do you think
it's possible that Virgil's also in some
ways pretty jealous of Dante because
they're both poets and then like Dante
is kind of like the chosen one and then
like also you mentioned earlier like
Beatatric is like very pretty and then
she asked Virgil to help and then
Virgil's like sure and so maybe he's a
bit jealous of Dante and then that's
also one of the reason why he want to be
in the upper position controlling him.
>> Any response to this? I I don't think so
because uh if you just try to be God it
must give up the hope right you give up
your ego so how come you just on the one
hand give up ego give up hope on the
other hand you also want to have envy or
you know have some kind of feeling like
that
>> but we said Virgil did not give up on
his hope I think
>> okay no I mean like if if you were
jealous of this guy what would you
push him in the water.
>> Yeah. You know, um I I I would think
Virgil would just say, "No, right. I'm
not going to help this guy." And and
also like you need to understand um it's
really hard for for you to appreciate
but at this time in history Virgil is
literally God. Every child is forced to
memorize um Virgil in school. No one who
knows who who Dante is. Okay? No one
knows who he is. No one cares who he is.
And Dante
uh told Virgil already, "Wow, you're my
hero. You're my god. I've been reading
you since I was young. I'm I'm a poet
because I aspire to be like you. Okay.
So So they can't possibly visual, oh my
god, he's better than I am. It's beyond
his imagination. Okay. All right. Let's
let's keep on going.
Verse 82.
And here advancing toward us in a boat
an aged man. His hair was white with
ears, was shouting, "Woe to you
corrupted souls. Forget your hope of
ever seeing heaven. I come to lead you
to the other shore, to the eternal dark,
to fire and frost, and you approaching
there, you living soul. Keep well away
from these. They are the dead." And when
he saw I made no move to go, he said,
"Another way, another harbors, not here,
will bring you passage to your shore. A
lighter craft will have to carry you."
Okay, so like hell is like literally the
worst school in the world. It's like
literally the worst school in the world.
It's very materialistic. There are lots
of rules. Um and the students are
treated like crap and the students have
given up all hope. And um the riverman
uh the fairy man who supposed to take
the souls across the the river sticks in
order to enter hell. Um he sees Dante
and says, "Wait a minute here, Dante.
You're not dead. You have a body. So
like don't get on my boat because the
rule is very simple. Only souls are
allowed to get on my boat. Go somewhere
else. Okay. Uh keep on going.
>> Verse 94. My guide my guide then. Karon,
don't torment yourself. Our passage has
been willed above where one can do what
he has willed and ask no more. Now
silence fell upon the woolly cheeks of
Caron Pilot of the livid marsh whose
eyes were ringed about with wheels of
flame. But all those spirits naked and
exhausted had lost their color and they
nashed their teeth as soon as they heard
Karon's cruel words. They execrated God
and their own parents and humankind and
then the place and time of their
conception seed and of their birth. Then
they forathered, huddled in one throng,
weeping along, weeping aloud along that
wretched shore which waits for all who
have no fear of God.
>> Okay. All right. So, um, Shaon is like,
"Dante, you're not dead. Get out of my
boat." And Virgil's like, "We have the
support of God." And God commands Dante
to
uh get on his boat. And Sean's like, "Oh
crap." Okay. But he agrees. Why is this
a paradox?
Why does this make no sense?
>> Because I feel like like Karan is a
mythical figure in Greek mythology. So
like if he's present then this
underworld is like the Greek underworld.
So he's he's not
supposed to be afraid of the Christian
God.
>> Yeah, that's exactly right. Like who
cares? Like this is the underworld,
right? God has no authority here.
So what does he obey?
The paradox is is this, right? Why is
Chiron a Greek mythical character? Why
is he obeying the Christian God?
It's a paradox.
He obeys
and he is afraid. Okay.
So, he fears God. So, but he's not
supposed to fear God. What's going on
here? Yes.
>> Who's Sheron again?
>> Um Cheron in Greek mythology is the
fairy man who takes you across the river
sticks into hell. Okay.
So why is he obeying?
>> Yes.
>> So at the end of City of God, Augustine
deals with this concept of of hell and
of evil. And he says that hell is not
evil because hell was created by God and
hell is a place of justice. And we have
this concept of hell is like Satan's the
ruler of hell, but God is the ruler of
hell because God create created hell.
And so I guess that's why he would be
afraid of it. It's because God is the
ultimate authority.
>> Yeah. But in paradise, we learn that
there are certain spots where God's like
doesn't shine. And one of these places
is is hell. So God doesn't really have
much presence here in hell. Yes.
>> Like there's a difference between
doesn't shine and doesn't shine at all.
Right? Like there is still this infant
testimony. There's this there's still
this tiny presence of God in hell and
God created hell because otherwise he
will not be God. Right? Because this
patch of hell does not belong to him. So
this patch of hell must still be
connected to him in some small way.
>> Okay? Okay. Look look let's not
overthink things. Okay? Like there's a
problem with like too much education.
You you tend to like overthink things.
Dante is a Democrat. He wants people, he
believes that anyone regardless of
education is able to reason out certain
things by himself. Okay? So try not to
be too sophisticated and just ask
yourself what's going on here. The
paradox is this. The paradox is that
um Sean should not be afraid of God. He
should not obey God. But he does obey.
Why?
It's a riddle. Yes.
>> Could it be that he's not actually like
um submitting to God but submitting to
Virgil?
Like because it's Virgil's words,
Virgil's command. So
>> who's speaking? It's Virgil. Do you
understand?
Do you understand? Doesn't matter what
Virgil is saying. It's Virgil speaking.
So Sharon is submitting to Virgil, not
to God.
You understand?
So who's the real master of hell? It's
Virgil is the master of hell. Okay. Here
he's telling us here Donn is telling us
Virgil is the master of hell.
Okay. Yes.
>> Is that why he chose not to go to
heaven?
>> Exactly. You understand? Do you
understand the logic of this? Because
you are emperor of hell and you go to
hell. Heaven and now you are servant to
God.
Does that make sense?
Yeah. Because you know from our
imagination I thought Lucifer who is the
you know the godfather in hell but how
how do you say that Virgil or you mean
Virgil just is kind of a avatar of a
demon or
well again this will be revealed to to
us over time. Okay but look what we know
is Virgil knows hell really really well.
Okay? Because he's able to guide Dante
throughout hell. That's number one.
Number two is the people in hell seem to
obey him. Right? That's number two.
Number three is we know for a fact that
he has the option of ascending to
heaven, but he chooses not to. Okay? So
again, that is the
um so Donn doesn't tell us outright, but
he but he forces you to make this
conclusion based on what you've read.
Okay. Yes.
>> So I I feel I feel like like there are
two things I want to talk about. The
first part is in answer to your question
about why Virgil is suddenly Satan. Like
>> I I didn't say Virgil is suddenly S. I
said it said that he seems to be master
of hell. I was answering the question. I
I was saying that it seems like he is an
emanation of the primal force of blind
obedience that is the master of hell.
Like he's just a avatar here. He's not
the actual king of hell. Uh and there is
no actual king of hell in physical body
down to walk with us. And the
>> No, no, no, no, no, no, no. You you
getting it confused theologically.
>> I uh let's uh move on. I have another
question. Uh so uh it's um
in this uh interaction between uh Sharon
and uh Virgil it is also an indication
of basically all the people uh in hell
are more obedient than people everywhere
else. So it's it's just a reflection of
the general passivity of of of people in
hell.
>> Um okay so we we have to be very
careful. Okay. Satan is Satan not
because he is the paragon of obedience.
What is Satan really?
What what is his problem? Yes.
>> Satan is Lucifer which used to be an
angel of music in the heavens and he was
more beautiful and talented than all the
other angels. So he grew proud and
decided to not listen to God.
>> Exactly. Okay. So the problem is not
obedience. The problem is pride. People
in hell are distinguished not by their
obedience, they're distinguished by
their pride.
That's why Chiron is so rude to Dante.
Right.
But
>> but when you're enter hell, don't you
have to abandon your pride or your ego?
>> If you're the soul, right? But Cheron is
is like one of the demons of hell. You
understand? He's the one who controls
hell, right? Right? So if you're a soul
entering hell, you must abandon all
hope. You must be completely passive.
But the people in charge, right, they're
proud. And so what what we will learn as
we go on is like there's actually a lot
of infighting in hell. Okay? So maybe
certain people obey Virgil, but others
don't obey Virgil. Okay? But Virgin
doesn't care because he's like, "I
rather be emperor of hell than uh
servant in heaven." And and and who who
else fought this?
What who else believed this?
>> Yeah. Right. Okay. That's why he he's in
hell. Yes.
>> So like this is something I don't get.
So like in a historical framework,
Virgil is human. Virgil has a soul. And
Dante definitely knows that Virgil is
human and has a soul. So if he Virgil is
down here that means that his soul must
have ended up down here. But you just
said that all souls who enter hell must
become passive. So why is he being so
active now?
>> Okay. All right. So um
in Donny's imagination,
Virgil is eternal.
He's immortal. Why?
Because people read his poetry, right?
So Virgil has become the poem the iniad
itself. Virgil is just the expression
of the poem the iniad. Okay. Does it
make sense? All right. Um let's like
like like like let we have a lot to do.
Okay. So so let's keep focused. Let
let's just try to get get as much on as
we can. Okay. Let's let's let's go.
>> Verse 109.
The demon Karen with his eyes like
embers by signal into them has all
embarked has or his ore strikes anyone
who stretches out as in the autumn
leaves detach themselves first one and
then the other till the bow sees all all
its fallen garments on the ground.
Similarly the e the evil seed of Adam
descended from the shoreline one by one
when signaled as a falcon called will
come. So do they move across the
darkened waters even before they reach
the farther shore. New ranks already
gather on this bank.
My son, the gracious master said to me,
those who have died beneath the wrath of
God, all these assemble here from every
country, and they're eager for the river
crossing because celestial justice spurs
them on so that their fear is turned
into desire.
No good soul ever takes its passage
here. Therefore, if Karon has complained
of you, by now you can be sure what his
words mean.
>> Okay, so this is a really hard idea for
us to appreciate. Okay, but the people
in hell when they cross the river, their
fear is turned into desire. Okay, so
maybe before they enter hell, they
didn't really uh understand what hell
is. They're they're afraid. They come to
the river crossing and like they really
want to enter hell. Okay. So, let's try
to figure out what hell really is. And
again, it's it's inverse of heaven.
Okay. Right. How is hell the inverse of
heaven? What what what's the difference
in Dante's conception?
Hell is circles. Heaven is fears.
Uh yes.
>> Oh
>> no. But but but I'm saying let's figure
out the governing principles of heaven.
Let's figure out the governing
principles of hell.
Uh yes.
>> Um hell is more about obedience which is
basically the AniAD and then heaven's
more of a reflection of the divine
comedy which is creativity
um and ego.
>> Yeah. So the the key is obedience. Okay.
If you are someone of pride like Virgil,
you need the way to express your pride
is if people obey you. You understand?
So hell is a place for two types of
people. People who want to control the
people and people who want to be
controlled.
And that's what hell is.
And heaven is a place of perfect
justice, of free will. Okay? You are
there because you choose to be there and
then you choose to submit to God because
God is perfect justice and you
understand that. Okay.
Uh yes.
>> Uh again, this is something I'm confused
about. So uh you said that you chose to
submit to God. So, how is you chose to
submit to God and you chose to submit to
Satan different in in actuality?
>> Okay. All right. Um, again, we're
running out of time, so I'll explain to
you really quickly. Okay. You choose God
because you have perfect knowledge of
the world and you think that God is the
best choice.
All right? So, it's one of knowledge.
It's one of love. Why did you choose
Satan? Because you're afraid. You don't
know anything. you're afraid. You rather
give up your free will than to engage in
a process of knowledge of of inquiry of
learning that enables you to understand
the cosmos. That's why you choose Satan
because it's the easiest path for you to
take. One of obedience is a lot harder
than self-doubt, self-discovery,
okay? Debate. Does that make sense,
guys? Okay. If you have perfect
knowledge, you're going to choose God.
You will I will choose simmit to God if
you have perfect knowledge. But that
that requires a lifetime of learning of
debate of um
yes
>> but how could you give away your free
will to Satan? Like if you you if you
can give give away God's most precious
gift to Satan, then Satan is just as
powerful as God
>> because it's free will. You can do
whatever you want.
>> Yeah. And you can give it away whenever
you want.
>> Yes. That's that's why it's called free
will.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Let's let's keep on going.
>> Verse 130. And after this was said, the
darkened plane quake so tremendously the
memory of terror then bathed me in sweat
again. A whirlwind burst out of the tear
drenched earth, a wind that crackled
with a blood red light. A light that
overcame all of my senses. And like a
man whom sleep has seized, I fell.
>> Okay, so this happens a lot. Okay.
Basically, Donnie gets blind in heaven
and then uh Donnie uh has Caesars
uh in uh in uh hell. Okay.
You know, you know this this is the
interesting
um
uh question. Do you think Donnie had
epilepsy?
You know, that that is a possibility,
right? Because back then if you have
epilepsy, they they really thought that
you were ceased by God and he had these
visions, right? Okay. So So that that is
a question for us to think about. We'll
never know. But but yeah. Uh yes.
>> Uh he most likely had shiso because he
kept hearing voices talking to him.
Yeah.
>> Oh, okay. And you know for that for a
fact.
>> Well, I know that he dreamt of an entire
other personality, Beatress, as an
adult, mind you. Not as a kid with
imaginary friend. So there's some kind
of disorder here.
>> Okay. Well, clear clearly there's a
disorder, but but what what it is, we we
we'll never know. Okay. All right. Let's
let's keep on going to Kendle four,
please.
Kendle four.
The heavy sleep within my head was
smashed by an enormous thunderclap, so
that I started up as one whom force
awakens.
I stood erect and turned my rested eyes
from side to side and I stared steadily
to learn what place it was surrounding
me. In truth I found myself upon the
brink of an abyss. The melancholy valley
containing thundering unending wailings.
That valley dark and deep and filled
with mist is such that though I gazed
into its pit, I was unable to discern a
thing. Let us descend into the blind
world now. The poet who was deathly pale
began. I shall go first and you will
follow me. But I who had seen the change
in his complexion said, "How shall I go
on if you're frightened, you who have
always helped dispel my doubts?" And he
to me, "The anguish of the people whose
place is here below has touched my face
with the compassion you mistake for
fear."
Let us go on the way that waits long. So
he set out and he had meme enter on that
first circle girdling the abyss. Here
for as much as hearing could discover
there was no outcry louder than the size
that caused the everlasting air to
tremble. The sight arose from sorrow
without torments out of the crowds the
many multitudes of infants and of women
and of men. The kindly master said, "Do
you not ask, who are these spirits whom
you see before you? I'd have you know
before you go ahead they did not sin and
yet though they have merits that's not
enough because they lacked baptism the
portal of faith that you embrace
and if they lived before Christianity
they did not worship God in fitting ways
and of such spirits I myself am one
for these defects and for no other evil
we now are lost and punished just with
this we have no hope and yet we live in
longing
>> okay so we are now in limbo okay which
is the first circle of hell and limbo.
It's actually a very nice place. It's a
very nice retiring community. Um but
it's not heaven because
why
why are these people in limbo rather
than in heaven? Yeah. They were not
baptized as Christians. Okay. So again,
this is Virgil being absolute. What he's
saying is like unless you were baptized,
you could never ever access heaven. And
this this again at this time in history
is what the Catholic Church teaches.
Yes.
>> I like it's Virgil who said that because
I'm not a I'm not baptized, I belong
here.
>> Exactly. Okay.
>> It's him castigating himself, not the
laws of the universe, it is it is
Virgil.
>> No, no, no, no, no, no. Virgin is being
absolute here.
>> Oh, he's being absolute here.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
They have merits, but that's never
enough. No matter how hard you work, no
matter how good you are, no matter how
virtuous you are, if you lack baptism,
the best place you can hope for is limbo
in uh hell. Okay. Uh yes,
>> I have a question because uh in the
stanzer is that uh people cannot be
perfectly uh baptized. What is that
mean? If it means [clears throat] that
only the baptized may be not enough. It
must be baptized perfectly. So what's
the difference?
>> Wait wait wait I
where does where what does spir say
that?
>> The the people should be um uh
>> what line are you referring to?
>> Perfectly baptized.
>> What line are you referring to?
>> Where does it say perfect?
>> Yesterday. Yesterday we we we saw that.
>> No no no no. Refer me to the line.
>> Okay. Okay. I mean today.
I can't remember exactly, but
>> No, no, no, no. Guys, guys, we're
referring to Virgil. You have to like
tell me what the line is. Line 35 says
what?
>> Because they lack baptism. There was no
perfect word in it.
>> There's no perfect word here.
It's It's that simple. Okay. If you were
baptized as a Christian, you are allowed
to go to heaven. If you're not baptized,
you don't go to heaven. It's pretty
simple. Okay.
Uh yes.
Yes.
>> Um so like if we we just talked about
the infants, right? And we figure out
why they were in heaven despite maybe
not being baptized. So like are these
all grown people down here? Are there
infants in this bunch?
>> There are infants. That's a question.
There are infants in here as well. Okay.
There are infants here as well. And and
Donnie will will explain will explain
this. All right. Let's keep on going.
Line 43.
Great sorrow ceased my heart on hearing
him for I had seen some estimable men
among the souls suspended in that limbo.
>> Okay. So again, Donnie doesn't
understand this. How is it possible that
in a just world where God is perfect
justice if you are not baptized and and
you could be a great man but you can't
access heaven. Okay. Um keep on going.
Verse 46. Tell me my master. Tell me
Lord. I then began because I wanted to
be certain of that belief which
vanquishes all errors. Did any ever go
by his own merit or others from this
place toward blessedness? And he who
understood my covert speech replied, "I
was new, entered on the state when I
beheld a great Lord enter here. The
crown he wore, a sign of victory. He
carried off the shade of our first
father, of his son Abel, and the shade
of Noah, of Moses, the obedient
legislator, of father Abraham, David the
king, of Israel his father, and his
sons, and Rachel she for whom he worked
so long, and many others. He made them
blessed and I should have you know that
before them there were no human souls
that had been saved.
>> Okay. So Dante asks is there an
exception to this? And then um what
Virgo says is yes there's only one
instance there's only one exception and
that's when Jesus came to hell for three
days. He took with him all the great
souls of the Bible including Adam,
Moses, David, everyone. Okay. uh they
were not baptized because they were
Israelites. They were they were uh Jews,
but because they were so great, uh Jesus
forgave them and took them to heaven
with him. But that's the only time.
That's it. Okay? And like again, we know
this is not going to be true. Over time,
as we read Divine Comedy, we're going to
find a lot of exceptions actually, but
here because uh it's Virgil and because
we're just reading Divine Comedy, we
think this must be true. Okay. So, so,
so we are under the impression that
everything he says is the absolute
truth. Okay, keep on going.
>> Verse 64.
We did not stay our steps. Although he
spoke, we still continued onward through
the wood. The wood, I say, where many
spirits thronged. Our path had not gone
far beyond the point where I had slept
when I beheld a fire went out against a
hemisphere of shadows. We still were at
a little distance from it, but not so
far I could not see in part that
honorable men possessed that place. Oh,
you who honor art and science both, who
are these souls whose dignity has kept
their way of being separate from the
rest? And he to me, the honor of their
name, which echoes up above within your
life gains heaven's grace, and that
advances them.
Meanwhile, there was a voice that I
could hear. Pay honor to the estimable
poet. His shadow which had left us now
returns.
After that voice was done, when there
was silence, I saw four giant shades
approaching us. In aspect, they were
neither sad nor joyous. My kindly master
then began by saying, "Look well at him
who holds that sword in hand, who moves
before the other three as lord. That
shade is Homer, the consmate poet. The
other one is Horus. Satirist. The third
is Avid and the last is Lucan.
Because of each of these spirits shares
with me the name called out before by
the lone voice. They welcome me and
doing that do well. And so I saw that
splendid school assembled led by the
Lord of song incomparable who like an
eagle soarses above the rest. Soon after
they had talked a while together, they
turned to me saluting cordially. And
having witnessed this, my master smiled.
An even greater honor than was mine, for
they invited me to join their ranks. I
was the sixth among such intellects.
>> So Donn is saying that he is in the
pantheon of the greatest poets. Okay,
keep on going.
>> Line 103. So did we move along and
toward the light, talking of things
about which silence here is just as
seemly as our speech was there. We
reached the base of an exalted castle
encircled seven times by towering walls
defended all around by a fair stream. We
forted this as if upon hard ground. I
entered seven portals with these sages.
We reached a meadow of green flowering
plants. The people here had eyes both
grave and slow. Their features carried
great authority. They spoke infrequently
with gentle voices. We drew aside to one
part of the meadow, an open place both
high and filled with light, and we could
see all those who were assembled. Facing
me there on the enameled green.
Greatarted souls were shown to me, and I
still glory in my having witnessed them.
I saw Electra with her many comrades,
among whom I knew Hector and Anias, and
Caesar in his armor falconeyed.
>> [snorts]
>> I saw Camila and Pen Penthicia and on
the other hand on the other side saw
King Latinas who sat beside Levvenia his
daughter. I saw that Brutus who drove
Tark went out Lricia Julia Marsh and
Cornelia and Solitary set apart Zadden.
When I had raised my eyes a little
higher and saw the master of the men who
know seated in philosophic family.
There I'll look up. There I'll look up
to him. I'll do honor. I'll do him
honor. There I beheld both Socrates and
Plato. Closest to him in front of all
the rest. Democrus who ascribes the
world to chance. Dioynes and Piticles
and Zeno and Thalus and Anaxagorus
Heraclitus. I saw the good collector of
medicinals. eyes mean Dioscordis and I
saw Orpheus and Tuli Lunus Moral Senica
and Uklit the geometer and Hypocrates
Hypocrates and Gallen Avisa Averos of
the great commentary
>> Aina and Avarles are Muslims okay these
are the great Muslim intellectuals of
the Islamic golden age uh keep on going
>> I cannot hear describe them all in full.
My ample theme impels me onward, so
what's told is often less than the
event. The company of six divides into
me knowing guide leads me another way
beyond the quiet into trembling air. And
I have reached a part where no things
gleams.
>> Okay. All right. Stop. Okay. All right.
So, what I'll do now is compare and
contrast heaven and hell. Okay. Um at
the very top
of heaven is of course is the imperium,
right? The imperium.
And the imperium
um is where God is. And for beside God
is the red rose, okay? Like the stadium
where the greatest souls of humanity
reside next to God. The queen is Mary.
But then uh sitting beside Mary is Eve
and you have Anna who is Mary's mother.
You have Beatatrice. You you have
Rachel. You have Rebecca. You have
Lucia. Okay. Okay. That is the highest
level of
um heaven. Now in inferno which is hell
the highest level is actually limbo
right?
Because we're descending downwards.
Okay. So the highest level is actually
limbo. And in limbo we have the greatest
heroes, thinkers, poets of humanity.
Okay? We have Julius Caesar, we have uh
um we have Homer, we have Socrates, we
have Plato, we have all the greatest
heroes of humanity.
Can someone explain to me why this is
constructed the way it is? What is
Donnie saying here? because they didn't
believe in God or they didn't uh they
weren't Christian.
>> Yeah, that's what Virgil says, right?
But we know Virgil is not a reliable
narrator. We have to use our own logic.
We have to like really think about the
cosmology at work here. Okay. Uh did did
you have a question or comment?
>> Yeah, because just now you said that the
great hero who just live in limbo,
right? because maybe they just uh
they're just just great hero, you know,
because they they don't need to love God
or maybe they they don't even know the
God. They just
>> I Yes, I I I know that's what Virgil
says. Okay. But but what I'm trying to
tell you is that Virgil lies all the
time. And what we know Yes.
>> Uh I think these people in hell live
through ego and so they wanted to be on
top of everyone whereas in Paradise they
are within God. So they're in the
center.
Right. No. Okay. So, so what you're
saying is that the people in limbo,
people like Julius Caesar, Homer
are selfish who want glory. And the
people in heaven, people like Mary, uh,
Rachel, they are without ego. I is that
what you're trying to say?
>> Uh, it was more about like how you
consider yourself. I think like in hell,
you're above everyone. you want to be
like in control and like have the level
of hierarchy where yeah you're just like
superior to them whereas in uh the
paradise you're within God so like
you're inside of him you're in the
center of him and you're all loving so
it's not about like rank or anything
>> okay yeah so so that's one explanation
where um the people in hell this limbo
they are trying to win glory for
themselves whereas as in heaven, these
people uh whether it's Anna, Mary, uh
Lucia, Beatatrice, or Rachel, they're
trying to spread love in the world.
Okay.
Yeah, that's that's one possibility.
Yes.
>> These people seem to be the smartest,
strongest, most powerful people. And so
in limbo, yes, they are.
>> And so that seems to be saying that you
can't force open the gates of heaven
with your logic, with your strength,
with your power.
>> Exactly. Yeah, that that's also another
possibility. Okay. Yes.
>> Or maybe because they they devoted their
lifetime into doing great things and
then they're selfless and then they
still have the hope that they could
potentially save the people in help. Is
that a possibility?
>> Could you repeat that? I'm not I'm not
sure I understand what
>> I'm saying like when they were alive
they devoted their lifetime into doing
something great that like for example
the poets acknowledge people of more
knowledge and then maybe they just chose
to be in hell because they still have
the hope that they could potentially
inspire or save some of the people over
there.
>> Uh no
actually I I I I don't Yeah.
>> Yeah. because uh before Christianity uh
all of the great hero would just been
born. So yeah this that's why they did
putting them into limbo because this is
before that right before the
Christianity which has been born. Okay
again like we're trying to understand
Dante and one way to understand Dante is
to use your imagination and create
contrast. Okay. So um Dante puts Mary,
Eve, Beatatrice, Anna, Rachel, and Lucia
at the very top. Okay. They are the
greatest heroes. Yes.
>> Paradise is all ladies or women and then
here is mostly great men. And I think
maybe some qualities that he sees in
them that separates the sexes. So like
the women are more submissive. They
worship God. They are not willing to be
the center. by these men they laid down
the foundation of intellectual world on
earth. So they are the centralized
either power, authority or foundation.
So they didn't want to center around God
like revolve around God.
>> Well, okay. Okay. So So um I I need to
correct her. Okay. These women are not
submissive. Beatric is not submissive.
Rachel is not submissive. Rebecca is not
submissive. They're all very strong uh
women. Okay. All right. So, so I want to
do this exercise.
If you were asked to pick people who
should be beside God in Imperium, okay,
who would you pick?
No, no, no, no, no. Be be these people
are pagans, right? Who would you pick?
Well, Homer is a pagan. I'm just saying
like like if if you if you just talk to
any Christian and like, okay, like who
should be next to God? What names would
you come up with?
>> H
>> Augustine.
>> Excuse me.
>> Okay. Augustine. Jesus. Uh Jesus. Yes.
>> I think I think you need to pick people
who are pleasing to God. Like we have to
consider God's role in all.
>> Who is the most pleasing to God?
David. Okay. Why is David not on this
list? It's David. If you read the Bible,
it's like David. Okay. David has to be
number one more than Jesus.
Do you understand? If you read the
Bible, it's David who's the most
pleasing to God. That's why Israel is
called the kingdom of David.
Okay? So, it's David that in the Jewish
tradition, who who's even actually more
important than David?
>> Moses.
>> Thank you. Why is Moses not on this
list? Right? So, you need David, you
need Moses, you need Jesus, you can
argue about Augustine. Okay. Who else
would you have?
>> Elijah.
>> Thank you. Yes, Elijah. Right. Because
Elijah, guys, actually ascended to
heaven to be with God.
Who else? Yes, Noah. Right. Who else?
Abraham. Thank you. Because Abraham is a
father of all three faiths.
Christianity,
uh, Islam and and and and Judaism. Okay.
Why are they not on the list? None of
them are. This is all very confusing.
Do you understand?
This creates a huge paradox for us. Why?
Okay. In limb we we understand Julius
Caesar, Homer,
uh the greatest thinkers, her heroes of
antiquity. Yes, we understand that. But
if that's the case, then logically in
the imperium next to God should be
David. He should be number one. Then it
should be uh Moses, Abraham, Elijah.
Um you can also say Enoch. Okay, if some
of you know your Bible, Enoch should be
on the list as well, right? Because
Enoch was the first to ascend to heaven.
So, what's going on here?
Do you understand?
If we are to
um create parallelism in structure, then
if the people in limbo are the greatest
of integrity, then in heaven, it should
be the greatest of the Bible, right? But
it's not. It's people who are barely
mentioned in the Bible.
Mary,
um,
Rebecca, Rachel, and Anna, Anna's not
even in the Bible.
Okay. Beatric is definitely not in the
Bible. Okay. So, what's going on here?
anyone?
>> I don't know. Maybe because they don't
really love uh God. They just obedience
to God. It doesn't mean they love God.
>> Oh, David do loves God. Okay. David
loves God.
And again, this all what the Bible
teaches you. Okay. If you're a
Christian, then you know God loves David
the most and David loves God the most.
Uh yes. Could it be like
>> on earth they had a form of power and
power corrupts?
>> Okay, that is uh true. But but but but I
mean like Moses, Noah, Abraham, Elijah,
we all know their stories, right?
>> Yes.
>> I think he didn't put like too high
figures so as like readers we don't
compare ourselves to them and so it
gives us access to heaven.
>> Thank you. Yes. Do you understand?
First and foremost, what makes Donnie
democ like the revolution is his
democratic nature. Do you understand?
Okay. Democratic
and egalitarian.
If you are to create a world of love,
you need these two principles.
Democratic and egalitarian. Okay. The
people in integrity, right, in limbo,
Julius Caesar. Who among us can be
Julius Caesar? None of us. Okay. But who
among us can be uh Beatatrice or Anna or
Rachel or Lucia? Well, any one of us.
It's just our choice to make the Julius
Caesar. The things that allow him to be
Julius Caesar are unique,
right?
Who can be a Homer? No one except Homer.
Who can be a Dante? No one. Okay. But we
can all choose to be a good person.
And if we choose to be a good person,
we will impact the world, the people
around us and be next to God.
Do you understand? So
um usually poetry is written to put you
in awe to make you fear, right? That's
what the idiot is about. But divine
comedy is most is meant to inspire you
to ascend to greater heights, not just
like the educated. It's like anyone.
That's why Divine Comedy was written in
Tuskin, Italian, not Latin. Because
Latin is a language of the elite. Tuskin
is a language of anyone and everyone.
Okay.
Okay. Does that make sense? Okay. So
again, uh yes. Um, I just can't
understand why if this book is meant to
be democratic, why does it have so many
references?
Like, it's really hard to read if you
don't know anything about the Bible or
everyone he's talking about.
>> Yeah, that's a great question. Okay. All
right. [clears throat]
So, um,
first of all, I hate to say this, but
people back here in the year 1300,
they're probably more educated than than
than we are today. Okay? It's hard for
us to read, but back then, if you're
educated, uh, you had access to a very
wide classical education. Okay, I I know
this is not what you're taught in
school. You're taught that, oh, back
there people are living in the dark
ages, they have no books. That's not
true. Okay, you know, it's not true
because of Dante. If like back then you
have any access to this knowledge, how
could he have written this? Okay, so
back then the most people didn't have
access to education. Most people could
only go to church, but for the elite,
for people of a certain background, the
middle class, basically, you had access
to much wider education than you have
today. Okay, that's uh point one. Point
two is like the divine is meant to be an
infinite universe onto itself. It's a me
it's meant for a place to explore
um for the rest of your life. So having
these different references, it's almost
incentivizing you to do research on your
own. Does that make sense? Right?
Because like he doesn't want a situation
where you just read it once, you're
like, "Okay, I got I got it. Thank you
very much." No, he wants you to keep on
going back and thinking about it,
exploring it in order to fully uh
appreciate it. Okay? And and the way he
does that is through beauty, right? I
mean, it's it's like Leonardo da Vinci
painting the Mon the Mona Lisa, right?
It's not like you go like, "Oh, all
right." No, you want it in your house so
you can look at it every day for the
rest of your life because it's so
beautiful, right? And the more you look
at it, the more complexity, the more
nuance, the more subtlety you see in the
Mona Lisa. Does that make sense? Okay.
So, that's the intention. Okay. All
right. But but yeah, I mean like like
like it's a very common misunderstanding
like during the dark ages they lost the
Greeks, they lost integrity and so uh
they had to bring it back from the
Islamic world. That's not true at this
like and and just think about this how
in any society the the elite are
educated educated differently from the
common people right this is true history
the elite are going to have more access
to education than uh the common people
mainly through tutors
right mainly through tutors okay all
right is that clear guys all right uh
let let's let's continue
yes
>> like this is something I wonder about
since you started reading all these
names. So like if Dante is operating in
the spirit of Renaissance humanism, if
he is bringing back the Greeks, even
though you said that's not entirely
true, but let's say that he is bringing
back the Greeks, why is he condemning
all of these Greek heroes, all of these
ancient heroes to hell?
>> They're not in hell. They're in limbo.
>> Well, they are kind of in hell. You just
said that limbo is a part of hell.
>> Virgil already told us, right? They are
there because they lack the Christian
faith.
>> Virgil, what Virgil said wasn't true.
>> Right? And so [clears throat] you can
choose in limbo to adopt the Christian
faith.
Do you understand? And when you read the
Divine Comedy, you will find certain
individuals who do do that. Um
um Ko, but but that that's that's when
we get to purgatory. Okay. You will find
that there are certain individuals who
should be in limbo but because of their
own choice they they adopted the
Christian faith they ascended to
purgatory and even one uh Rifius will
ascend to heaven. Okay. All right. Let's
keep on going. Count five.
KTO five.
So I descended from the first enclosure
down to the second circle. That which
girdles less space but grief more great.
that goats to weeping. There dreadful
Mino stands nashing his teeth, examining
the sins of those who enter. He judges
and assigns and his as his tail twine. I
mean that when the spirit born to evil
appears before him, it confesses all and
he the connoisseur of sin can tell the
depth and hell appropriate to it. As
many times as Minos wraps its tail
around himself, that marks the sinner's
level. Always there's a crowd that
stands before him. Each soul in turn
advances toward that judgment. They
speak and hear, then they're cast below,
arresting his extraordinary task. Minos,
as soon as he had seen me, said, "Oh,
you who reached his house is suffering,
be careful how you enter whom you trust.
The gate is wide, but do not be
deceived."
>> Okay, this is like really interesting,
right? So Mino's the the monitor what
what he's doing is he's assigning people
to hell. Okay.
Mino sees Dante and Virgil and he says,
"Uh, be careful who you enter. Be
careful who you trust. Do not be
deceived." What is he referring to?
>> Don't trust a virginally.
>> Yeah. Okay. I I I would think that
because think about this logically. He's
saying like don't trust anyone in hell.
I'm done. Like I'm going to trust anyone
in hell. Thank you very much. Who's the
only person who can possibly trust? And
it's Virgil, right? He's saying don't
trust anyone. Okay? So it's a direct
reference to Virgil.
Okay? But it's impossible to see because
it's a paradox for you, right? Uh and so
and and so and so again, it's all
nuance. It's all subtlety.
Because
um I'm not sure if you ever had if you
ever try to convince someone right of
anything um um I mean you you you
probably know this right right Carol
where like like if you know your sons
are doing anything bad if you tell them
directly they they'll just keep on doing
that crap right but you have to do it in
a very nuanced way you have to nudge
that person right and and this is this
is what's happening here in comedy where
Don is nudging us right like okay I
understand Virgil is gone, but you know,
maybe he's not that honest. Okay, it's
all nudging. It's all nuance. It's all
subtlety. Okay, let's keep on going.
Line 21.
To which my guide replied, but why
protest? Do not attempt to block his
faded path. Our passage has been willed
above where one can do what he has
willed and ask no more.
>> Yeah, you see how Virgil gets angry now,
right? Because Virgil knows Minos is
telling Donnie, "Don't trust Virgil."
And like Virgil saying to him, "Shut up,
man."
>> Okay.
>> Yes.
>> Is Is Minos the Minotaur or the King of
Creed?
>> Yes. Yes.
>> I thought he was like the king of Cre I
just don't know why he's turned into a
monster.
>> No. No. Uh Minos is not the No. King
Minos is the king of Cre, right? The
monitor is the um is the monster that
that that protects the labyrinth. So
this is the monitor.
Okay,
let's uh go on
verse 25. Now notes of desperation have
begun to overtake my hearing. Now I come
where mighty lamentation beats against
me. I reached a place where every light
is muted, which bellows like the sea
beneath the tempest when it is battered
by opposing winds. The hellish hurricane
which never rests, strives on the
spirits with its violence, wailing and
pouting it in harasses them. When they
come up against the ruined slope, then
their cries and wailing and lament, and
there they curse the force of the
divine. I learned that those who undergo
this torment are damned because they
sinned within the flesh, subjecting
reason to the rule of lust. And as in
the cold season darling's wings bear
them along in broad and crowded ranks,
so does that blast bear on the guilty
spirits.
Now here now there, now down, now up, it
drives them. There's no hope that ever
comforts them. No hope for rest and none
for lesser pain. And just as cranes in
flight will chant their lays array their
long file across the air. So did the
shades I saw approaching borne by that
assailing wind lament and moan. So that
I asked him, "Master, who are those who
suffer punishment in this dark air?"
>> Okay, so we're in the first c first
circle of hell. Okay, like we we left
limbo uh and and now we are in hell
where proper where everyone's being
punished. Okay, in the first um circle,
these are people who lust. And the great
thing about Dante is he's so imaginative
like everyone who is guilty of a
particular sin has deserves has a just
punishment in hell. Okay. So these are
people who lust which means that they
constantly change their emotions. Right?
So the punishment is they're being
whipped around in a whirlwind. Okay.
Right.
So they are never they are they are not
loyal to their own emotions and now
they're just being whooped around in in
a whirlwind. Okay. Does that make sense?
Okay. All right. Let's keep on going.
Line 52.
the first of those about whose history
you want to know. My master then told me
once ruled as empress over many nation.
Her vice of lust became so customary
that she made license listed in her laws
to free her from the scandal she had
caused. She Seuramis of whom we read
that he was Nunis's wife and his
successor. He helped the land the Sultan
now commands. The other spirit killed
herself for love and she betrayed the
ashes of Sikius. The wanting Cleopatra
follows next. See Helen, for whose sake
so many years of evil had to pass. See
great Achilles, who finally met love in
his last battle.
>> Okay. All right. So, something that um
is confusing for people is that Dante
does not have access to Homer and the
Greeks. Okay. Um and so when you talk
about Achilles, he's not talking about
Achilles from the Iliad. He's talking
about Achilles from other uh mythologies
written in Latin. Okay. So this is why
it's a bit confusing for people. All
right. So um
something really uh you guys need need
to appreciate is what Virgil is doing is
he's naming these individuals in this
circle of lust.
And there's one person he doesn't name.
The other spirit killed herself for love
and she betrayed the ashes of Psychius.
Okay, he doesn't name this person, but
he does name Cleopatra. He names Helen,
names Achilles, he names Sarah Ramas.
Okay, so there's a thousand people.
There's only one person he does not he
does not name. Does anyone know who this
person is who killed herself for love
and she betrayed her husband? Sarakias
do.
>> It's Ditto. Okay, it's Ditto. Who
created Ditto?
Virgil.
>> Virgil. Okay. So, again, it's so
interesting um the contrast, right?
Because you have two great poets
uh in the line comedy. They are of
course Virgil and Dante. [snorts] Virgil
and Dante.
And both of them will create two great
female protagonists that are celebrated
throughout history. Virgil will create
Ditto
and Donna will create Beatatric.
If you read the Iniad, and we will read
the Iniad actually later this afternoon,
parts of it. Okay. What Virgil does is
he condemns Ditto to hell.
And then what Donnie does is
beat he will elevate Beatric to heaven.
Okay.
So there's abely no way that Dante
admires Virgil, right? I mean, he may
have read uh Virgil and be heavily
influenced by Virgil, but ultimately
embedded within the Divine Comedy is
this cosmic battle between Virgil and
Dante. Okay, we know because of how they
treat their different um heroes.
All right. And
um um actually we're running out of
time. So but I what what I want to do is
read certain passages of the Iniad.
Okay. So you can see who Ditto is and we
can contrast this with how Dante treats
Beatatric.
All right. Uh but are there any
questions about uh Yes,
>> I collect two questions from online
participants.
>> Okay. Uh the first one is could dentist
whole journey be read as the movement
from fragmentation to coherence. Uh hell
is equal to misaligned desire. Part uh
partic uh purgatory uh is uh like
purified desire. Paradise is something
like individual will uh fully aligned
with the dean order.
>> That that is a great point. Yes, it is a
journey and it's one from uh disunityity
to one of unity. Okay. And and it's
obvious because hell everyone's fighting
each other. Okay? Even though V Virgil
is kind of in charge, not everyone obeys
him and there's all of a trill going on,
right? So Mos is saying Dante, hey this
guy, Virgil, don't trust him. And
Virgil's like, "Shut up." Okay? And we
we'll see a lot of this disunityity in
hell. But when we go to heaven, we will
see that it is we we've been to heaven
and like so we know it is coherent. We
we know that is unified and everyone's
speaking with one voice. Okay. On behalf
of God. Yes.
>> The other question is uh could an
afterlife of complete nothingness for
eternity be the worst version of hell?
>> Uh could you repeat that? I I I didn't
catch that. Could an afterlife of
complete nothingness for eternity be the
worst version of hell?
>> After nothing
>> afterlife
>> of complete nothingness
>> of complete what? How do you spell that
word?
>> Nothing.
>> Nothing. Yes.
>> Would the afterlife be nothingness in
eternity?
Be the worst version of hell.
>> Be the worst version of hell.
>> No Wi-Fi.
>> Um, so
um,
okay. So there are two conceptions of of
hell, right? Hell as a place where you
feel nothing, where nothing happens.
It's just complete absence. people
forget who you are. You You cease to
exist. [clears throat]
And hell is a place where people are
being punished for
uh things that they did uh for all of
eternity. What do you think is worse?
>> Uh yeah,
is much worse than just being annalated.
I think the person is saying
annihilation of the soap like you just
go into nothing but then you don't get
punished for anything you did in on
earth. So I think suffering in hell
would be much worse.
>> Uh yes
you you said the first one.
>> Yeah. I think I think I mean like at
least in the second one you're being
tortured, right? You got something to do
with you can and you can still feel I
feel like the first one you can you can
you literally can feel nothing. and I
will choose the second over the first
one.
>> Uh, yes.
>> I feel like this kind of sounds like the
layer where like the unbaptized are in
because they're basically sighing and
then like they're they don't receive
physical punishment,
>> you know, that's a really um uh No, no,
no, no. I mean, like L limbo is is
basically like a very nice place. Okay.
It's not a punishment. Okay.
All right. Um, uh, yes.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I think the, uh, limbo is
kind of thing just like waiting room,
right? You don't know what happened.
>> No, it's not a waiting room. It's a
retirement community.
>> Okay.
>> It's a very nice retirement. That's like
literally what it is. Okay. Yes.
>> So, um, Augustine would say that
in hell you still have your ego and your
ego, this is the Schopenhauer idea, the
will to live. Yeah. So, the ego refuses
to give up no matter what. So in in
hell, they couldn't even wrap their mind
around this idea of of an ether of an
annihilation because you're going to be
somewhere.
>> And so if they don't, they're in hell
because they are turning away from God.
They would they would feel
>> whatever. They don't want to be near
God. And so they're in hell because it's
the furthest place from God, but they
don't want to be nothing because they
still want to be an ego.
>> Yeah. So this is a really hard problem
to solve. Um because I think intuitively
being annalated, being lost forever,
like people don't remember who you are,
it's actually the worst thing because
even if you're in hell, there is a bit
of hope, right? Um it is you're still
part of the cosmos, but to be annalated
means that your soul is now not
dissipated. It's like you you're gone
forever. Okay. So I so so I I would
agree with that thought like the idea of
annihilation is the worst possible thing
to happen and how do you live a life of
annihilation? What leads you to to
annihilation?
So bring back this this Dante. What
allows you to to be forgotten?
Come on. Yes.
>> Send you anywhere? Oh or you lost your
ego completely? You don't want you want
to know why you forgot it.
No one loves you.
>> That's not because no one loves you.
>> You're not living by the principle of
ulamonia and arity. Okay?
>> Because you've lived a pointless life.
You understand? Because your life you
just chose the easiest thing to do. No
one remembers who you are. Maybe your
family does, but over time your family
will will will forget who you are. Okay.
So um it's implied
um in the line comedy that most of us
will be annihilated. Okay? Most of us
won't even make it to hell because you
you you needed to do something with your
life to make it to hell. And if you did
nothing in your life, then that's
actually worse than hell. You'll just be
forgotten. And in fact um if you read
the divine comedy very closely
um there are certain individuals that
you think should appear in a certain
place but doesn't and that's a very
powerful technique that Dante uses in
order to criticize certain individuals.
Okay. Okay. So, for example, um in uh
heaven, yes, I understand uh um uh David
should be next to uh God, but he's not
next to God. He is in heaven, but he's
not next to God. Um and and and he he'll
be using that a lot. Another thing is
remember the person that
uh Donna is is most responding to is
Augustine.
and Augustine is never quoted in the
divine comedy, right? It's almost a form
of annihilation. Uh
did you have a question? Okay. All
right. Okay. So, yeah. So, that's
something that Don will will tell us.
Okay. You have a responsibility to live
your life to the fullest because if you
don't, you'll be forgotten and that's
even worse than hell. Okay. It's
complete annalation. Okay. All right. Uh
thank you uh to the live stream for
these two two questions. We'll come back
in an hour. Okay. All right. So welcome
back. [clears throat] And uh to start
class, I want to emphasize a point which
is at the very heart of the line comedy
is a radical democratic spirit. So if we
look at hell, it's basically a um
allegory of the world he's living in,
right? where everyone's fighting for
power and where um everyone uh is
obedient and passive and afraid. Um so
hell is the best description of the
world he's living in. And for Dante, the
answer is
um a radical democracy in which everyone
has access to knowledge and to learning.
for Dante. Uh it doesn't matter who you
are. It doesn't matter what the results
are, what you achieve. What matters is
how you choose to live your life. That's
why at the very at the very top of
heaven are people like ROF, uh Rachel,
Anna, ordinary people who didn't really
accomplish much, but who chose to live a
life of faith, hope, and love. And
that's what he's trying to she's trying
to do. He's trying to inspire people to
live their best life um regardless of
their circumstance.
And the divine comedy that the the
reason why there's so many references
embedded in the the divine comedy is an
act of faith telling people listen all
the knowledge you need to understand God
is in here. If you make the effort, if
you act with faith, love, and hope you
will be able to access heaven yourself.
Okay? So that that that at the very
heart of the divine harmony is a
democratic spirit. This goes against the
elitist mentality of the iniad where the
principal virtue that the iniad is
trying to convey is piety, obedience.
Don't think for yourself. Don't trust
your intuition. Just obey
the um word of God. Just do what the
gods tell you and things will turn out
proper. Okay. So, um the Iniad it's
really a struggle of one hero Inas to
discover this truth to discover that
it's your emotions, your intuition, your
imagination that leads you astray. What
sets you on the straight path is
obedience to uh the gods. Okay. Piety.
So how the iniat starts is um
Troy's destroy because of the Trojan
horse
and Inas who loves Troy wants to
um rescue his people but the the Greeks
are so dominant right and so Venus his
mother parish says there's a mission for
you and your miss and the mission is to
take your son to Italy and you will and
your family will build the empire of
Rome and Inas um um obeys. He sees Helen
of Troy and he thinks that it's Helen of
Troy that's caused all his misery. So so
what this is I mean and I mean the thing
about the iniad is it's explicit. Okay,
it's very hard to interpret the Iniad
incorrectly.
Um but the idea is that Helen Troy
caused all this destruction which means
that love caused all this destruction,
right? This is love is a disease that
destroys civilization.
Um and then Inas obeys and returns home
and him and his family are escaping.
They're going to ships and his wife
Kisha decides to kill herself. Why?
Because Creia understands that um in
Italy Inas must marry into royal lo
local royalty in order to found a new
dynasty. So she must kill herself in
order to make this possible. So that's
what wives should do. If the husband
needs to like you know marry her up then
like you should just like you know kill
yourself right. Um now Inias goes to
Italy but the queen
of the gods uh Hera um she's called Jo
in the Iniad because of Latin she's she
he's she's angry at Inas and she plots
to destroy him. Okay so like right away
you understand all the chief villains in
the Iniad are female. Okay, whether it's
Helen McCroy, whether it's Jove. Um,
[snorts] and so Inas gets shipwrecked in
Carthage. And there he meets the local
queen Ditto. And Ditto falls in love
with him. He falls in love with her. And
Inas just wants to settle down in
Carthage and live a happy life. The gods
get really angry at him and says,
"Indius, you We gave you a simple
mission. Go to Italy. What are you doing
here in Carthage?" And Inas obeys. and
Ditto is heartbroken and she's so
heartbroken that um she kills herself.
Okay, for but before she kills herself
she makes a vow and her vow is we the
Carthan genians will always try to
destroy Rome. Okay, because it has broke
my heart and so my as I die my final
wish to my people is to always set war
on Rome. This is important because
historically
Rome will destroy Carthage, right? But
what uh Virgil is saying is well the
blame isn't us Romans. The blame is
Ditto because she's this crazy
Okay? And love is just a disease. All
right? So again, thematically it's not
that hard to interpret um the Iniad. and
the Iniad becomes a basis for Western
civilization for about a thousand years
uh until the rise of Dante. So what I
want to do is I want to read certain
passages from the Iniad. Okay. So uh
we're going to uh so let me set the
scene. Um Ditto and Inas already
married. They already had sex. They're
betrod to each other. And the gods tell
Inas, you have to uh go to Italy. So
Inias being a guy decides, "Oh, I'll
just sneak sneak away. Okay, I'm not a
tell ditto. I'm going to sneak away."
But she's queen of Carthage and she kind
of figures out very quickly. Oh, Inas is
trying to sneak away. He's trying to run
away. Okay, so she confronts Inias and
this is what she says. Okay.
>> At last, she sails the ears before
[clears throat] he said he said a word.
So you traitor, you really believe you'd
keep this a secret, this great outrage,
steal away in silence from my shores.
Can nothing hold you back? Not our love,
not the pledge when sealed with our
right hands. Not even the thought of
dedo doomed to acrue death. Why labor to
rig your fleet when the winter's raw to
risk the deep when the north winds
closing in? You cruel, heartless, even
if you were not pursuing alien fields
and unknown homes, even if ancient Troy
were standing still. Who would sail for
Troy across such heaving seas? You're
running away from me. Oh, I pray you by
these tears, by the faith in your right
hand. What else have I left myself in
all my pain? By our wedding vows, the
marriage we began. If I deserve some
decency from you now, if anything mine
has ever won your heart, pity a great
house about to fall. I pray you if
prayers of any place reject these this
scheme of yours. Thanks to you, the
African tribes, Numidian warlords hate
me. Even my own Tyrions rise against me.
Thanks to you, my sense of honor is
gone. Me one and only pathway to the
stars, the renown I once held dear. In
whose hands my guest you leave me here
to meet my death.
>> Okay. So, Ditto is a marshing any and
says like I love you. I give you
everything. Okay. I am all yours and you
choose to run away. Once you are gone, I
will have no honor. Everyone will laugh
at me. They will come and they will all
these different warlords that once were
afraid of me. The warrior queen. Uh they
will come and they will kill me. They
will steal my throne. They'll probably
rape me. Okay, so pity me. Okay, it's
it's one of anger, but also one of pity.
All right. Uh, let's continue.
>> Guest, that's all that remains of
husband now. But why do I linger on
until my brother picon batters down my
walls or Yarbas drags me off his slave?
If only you'd left a baby in my arms,
our child before you deserted me. some
little Anias playing about our halls
whose features at least would bring you
back to me in spite of all. I would not
feel so totally devastated, so
destroyed.
>> So, she's lost all her honor. She's lost
um her pride. She's lost even her ego.
She's begging him like, "If you're going
to run away, at least impregnate me so
that at least I have a memory of you."
Okay, that's how desperate and pitiful
she's become. Um, given this, if you're
any how should you respond
if you were in a situation? Okay. How
how well how should you respond?
Well, the human response is to try to
comfort her, right? To say, you know,
I'm sorry. I love you, but the gods gave
me this mission. I'm afraid of the gods,
and so I'll come back or something.
Okay, but you make something up, right?
Um, but Inas doesn't do that. Okay,
let's let's keep on going.
The queen stopped, but he, warned by
Jupiter, now his gaze held steady,
fought to master the torment in his
heart. At last he ventured a few words.
I, you have done me so many kindnesses,
and you could count them all. I shall
never deny what you deserve, my queen.
never regret my memories of ditto. Not
while I can recall myself and draw the
breath of life. I'll state my case in a
few words. I never dreamt I'd keep my
flight a secret. Don't imagine that. Nor
did I once extend a bridegroom's torch
or enter into a marriage pack with you.
>> Right. All right. Sorry. So, um he's
lying. Okay. First of all, he did marry
uh her and also he is trying to keep his
escape a secret. Okay. So the guy's act
is an but he's also a
manipulator. Keep on going.
He's gaslighting her basically.
If the fates had left me free to live my
life, to arrange my own affairs of my
own free will. Troy is the city first of
all that I'd safeguard. Troy and all
that's left of my people whom I cherish.
The grand palace of Pam would stand once
more. With my own hands I would fortify
a second Troy to house my Trojans in
defeat. But not now Paul's oracle says
that I must seize on Italy's noble land.
His Lysian lot said say Italy there lies
my love. There lies my homeland. Now if
you a Phoenician fix your eyes on
Carthage, a Libyan stronghold. Tell me
why do you grudge the Trojans their new
homes on Italian soil? What is the crime
if we seek far off kingdoms too?
>> Okay, so this great hero Inias, he's
just an abusive right? Because
he's telling her um he's gaslighting her
first of all, but he's also saying like
if I had a choice, if it were really my
choice, I wouldn't even be with you,
okay? I'd be back in Troy some doing
something. Okay, that that's my that's
where my heart is. So, it's the gods who
forced me to come here. It's the gods
that forced me to go to Troy. It were
actually it were my choice, I wouldn't I
would not even want you. Okay. Uh so, of
course, yeah, he's an Thank
you. I know. Uh but this is the this is
the iniad. Um and so, uh D
um spends her all her time in her room
and she's not able to sleep. Okay. And
so she commits on a path to suicide.
Okay. So, so can you can you read
Torn in spirit did I will not dissolve
into sleep. Her eyes her mind won't
yield tonight. Her torments multiply
over and over. Her passion surges back
into heaving waves of rage. He she keeps
on brooding. Obsessions royal her heart.
And now what shall I do? Make a mockery
of myself? Go back to my old suitors.
Tempt them to try again. Back the
Numidians gravel plead for a husband.
though time and again I scorn to what
they're like.
>> Okay, sorry. Um, sorry. So, some
background. Okay, so Ditto is from
Phoenicia and she lost a power struggle
against her brother. Her brother killed
her husband Sakius. Ditto escapes to
Carthage and she builds this great city
Carthage and all the local warlords,
African warlords admire her and uh the
legend is they propose marriage to her.
In response, she decides to kill
herself. Okay, she builds a p and she
burns herself alive. Uh, and she becomes
in the eye of the carpets the great
warrior queen. Okay, someone who loves
her husband so much, someone who loves
her people so much that she would rather
die than yield than surrender and and
because of her of her example, because
of her legacy, she becomes
um the founder of the greatest empire of
Africa at this time. Okay. So, this is
how Ditto is remembered historically.
And what Virgil is doing is she he's
changing the legacy of Ditto to make her
this pathetic
um you know, betrayed uh woman. Okay,
keep on going.
>> What then? Trail the Trojan ships bent
to the Trojans's every last demand. So
pleased are they with all the help, the
relief I lent them once. And memory of
my service past stands firm in grateful
minds. And even if I were willing, would
the Trojans allow me to board their
proud ships? A woman they hate? Poor
lostful. Can't you sense it? Grasp it
yet. The treachery of La Medan's breed.
What now? Do I take flight alone,
consorting with crews of Trojan orsmen
and their triumph? Or follow follow them
out with all my troops of Tyrion
thronging the decks?
Yes. Hard as it was to uproot them once
from tire, how can I force them back to
sea once more? Command them to spread
their sails to the winds. No. No. Die.
You deserve it. End your pain with the
sword. You, my sister, you were the
first one over by my tears to pile these
sorrows on my shoulders. Mad as I was to
throw me into my enemy's arms. If only
I'd been free to live my life. Untested
in marriage, free of guilt as some wild
beast, untouched by panks like these. I
broke the faith. I swore to the ashes of
Zikius.
>> Okay, so as you can see, she is
completely insane now. Okay, she's she
uh love has driving her insane. So
again, the idea here is that love is a
curse. It's a disease. You fall to it
and your mind will shatter. Okay. So,
she's basically decided to cure herself
and she wants to kill herself in a way
that Inas will see because what her last
will is is to be be remembered by Inas,
right? And the way that the way that
she's going to force her memory onto
Inas is to kill herself in front of him.
The gods know that what her what her
intention is. So, they warn Inas like,
"Get out of here now. like do not
observe her dab because that it will
haunt you for the rest of your life.
Okay. Uh keep on reading.
Such terrible grief kept breaking from
her heart as Anas leapt in peace on his
ship's high stern. Bent on departing now
all tackle set to sail. And now in his
dreams it came again. The god his
phantom. The same features shining clear
like mercury head to foot. the voice,
the glow, the golden hair, the bloom of
youth on his limbs, and his voice rang
out with warnings once again. Son of the
goddess, how can you sleep so soundly in
such a crisis?
>> So, while
um Ditto is going crazy
and she's lamenting, what is Inas doing
right now?
>> He's sound asleep, man. He doesn't He
could care less, man. I keep on going.
Can't you see the dangers closing around
you now, mad man? Can't you hear the
west wind ruffling to speed you on? That
woman spawns her plots, mulling over
some desperate outrage in her heart,
lashing her surging rage. She's bent on
death. Why not flee headlong? Flee
headlong while you can. You'll soon see
the waves, a chaos of ships, lethal
torches flaring, the whole coast ablaze.
If now a new dawn breaks and finds you
still mingering on these shores. Up with
you now. Enough delay. Woman's a thing
that's always changing shifting like the
wind. With that he vanished into the
black night. Then terrified by the
sudden phantom and wrenching himself
from sleep leaps up and rouses his crews
and spurs them head headlong on. Quick
up and at it. Shipmates man the thwarts
spread canvas fast. A gods come down
from the sky once more. I've just seen
him urging us on to sever our mooring
cables. Sail at once. We follow you,
blessed God. Whoever you are, glad at
heart, we obey your commands once more.
Now help us. Stand beside us with all
your kindness. Bring us favoring stars
in the sky to blaze our way.
>> Okay, so again, Inias has been warned by
the god. So he's fle fled the scene.
Ditto has committed to killing herself
and she will make a final prayer before
she kills herself. Okay. Uh, can you
read please?
>> That is my prayer, my final cry. I pour
it out with my own lifeblood. And you,
my Tyans, Harry with hatred, all his
lie, his race to come. Make that
offering to my ashes. Send it down
below. No love between our peoples ever.
No packs of peace. Come rising up from
my bones, you avengers still unknown to
stop those Trojan settlers. Hunt with
fire and iron now or in time to come
whenever the power is yours. Shore clash
with shore, sea against sea, and sword
against sword. This is my curse. War
between all our peoples, all their
children, endless war.
>> Okay. So, one of the great tragedies of
antiquity is the destruction of
Carthage. Okay. uh Rome and Carthage
fought for dominance over the
Mediterranean and they will fight they
they fought three wars in the last war
the last the third Punic war Rome
extinguishes it annaliates Carthage from
the planet okay and so um at this time
Carthage is a great civilization
and um the Romans now have explained why
this happened and now Virgil explains
it's because love
uh took hold of Ditto,
destroyed her mind and it made her so
angry that not only did it did they
condemn her to death but they condemn
her entire people to death. It is
because of this madness that is why the
Carthaginians attacked Rome and Rome had
to defend itself and Rome recognized
that only by defeating and destroying
all of Carthage can Rome ever be saved.
Okay, so this is the madness of love.
Not only it will condemn you to death,
but it will condemn your entire
civilization to death. Okay, so Ditto
kills herself. And now what's going to
happen is that basically Inas has
forgotten her, right? Because Inas has
this mission from the gods and he he and
he he understands that in order to
fulfill his mission, he needs a
prophecy. He needs to talk to his father
who is dead. He needs to go into the
underworld to receive this prophecy.
when he goes to the underworld, who does
he meet? Ditto. Okay. Right. So, so, so
this is going to be their last encounter
together.
And let's see what happens to Ditto.
Right.
And wandering there among them, wounds
still fresh, Venetian ditto drifted
along the endless woods. As the Trojan
hero paused beside her, recognized her
through the shadows, a dim misty figure
as one, when the month as young may see
or seem to see the new moon rising up
through banks of clouds. That moment,
Anas wept and approached the ghost with
tender words of love. Tragic, ditto. So,
was the story true that came my way? I
heard that you were dead. You took the
final measure with a sword. Oh, dear
God. Was it I who caused your death?
>> What an this guy is, right? He's
like, "Was it me? Did you care for me? I
I didn't know."
Okay. It doesn't get worse than this.
Okay.
>> All right. Keep on going.
I swear by the stars, by the powers on
high, whatever faith one swears by here
in the depths of earth. I left your
shores, my queen, against my will. Yes,
the will of the gods that drives me
through the shadows. Now these
mouldering places so for Lauren, this
steep, unfathomemed night, their decrees
have forced me on. Nor did I ever dream
my leaving could have brought you so
much grief. Stay a moment. Don't
withdraw from my sight. Running away
from whom? This is the last word that
fate allows me to say to you, the last.
Anias, with such appeals, with welling
tears, tried to soothe her rage, her
wild fiery glance. But she, her eyes
fixed on the ground, turned away, her
features no more moved by his pleas as
he talked on. Then if she were set in
stony flint or Peran marble rock. And at
last she tears herself away. His enemy
forever fleeing back to the shadowed
forest where Sikias her husband long ago
answers all her anguish. Meets her love
with love. But Anias no less struck by
her unjust fate escorts her from afar
with streaming tears and pies her as she
passes.
>> Okay. So uh in is trying to have a
conversation with her but she does not
speak. Okay. Why this is important is
that at this time in history the
difference between a free individual
okay a citizen and a slave is that a
citizen has the right to speak. Okay a
citizen is literally someone who has the
right to speak before other people. So
losing speech, losing the capacity to
speak. It is worse than death. It is
slavery. Okay. So, love has not only
killed Ditto and killed her
civilization, but it's made her a slave.
Okay. All right. So, let's think about
this. Okay. This is the Iniad. Uh, this
is Virgil writing about Ditto.
Did Virgil know Ditto in real life?
>> Oh, I mean like I I mean I Okay. Sorry.
Sorry. Sorry, I I put this I phrased it
incorrectly. Okay.
Um,
who is Ditto?
Who who is she? We know who Beatus is,
right? But who is Ditto?
Yeah, I understand that. Right. But like
when you write, you have to use a model,
right? So So who who do you think Ditto
is really?
Excuse me.
Um, Rojo's muse. I would say it's the
opposite. Why?
Why?
If you have a muse, what are you doing?
You're praising her, right? But here,
uh, Virgil is showing how mad Ditto is.
So, who So, who do you think this person
is?
H
>> his ex,
>> right? His it could it could be an
ex-wife.
>> But but what but I mean like clearly
Virgil hates this person, right?
Otherwise, you can't write like this. So
what did she do to make Virgil angry at
her? Yes.
>> Maybe she is an example to him. like
he's trying to use her as an example to
maybe not betray a bunch of people for
your love.
>> Okay, so we've already established in
order for Dante to write about Beatric,
Beatric had to be a real person. Okay,
there had to be real emotions between
these two people. So Ditto is a real
person and it could be an ex-wife, but
something had to happen in order for
Virgil to hate her this much. And what
was it? probably
>> Virtual was probably embarking on his
own personal journey, but felt that she
was impeding him by being overly
emotional.
>> Um, no. I don't think I don't think
that's what it is. Yes.
>> Oh, I know it. She was unfaithful to
him.
>> Yeah. She betrayed him, right? You
understand? This sort of hatred can only
be generated through treachery,
right? or possibly even denial, right?
Where she he Virgil wanted her to be his
muse. He wanted to write poetry uh about
her and she's like, "Virgil, you're kind
of ugly, man. Get away from me, please.
You're stalking me now. I want to call
the police. Don't bother me anymore.
Okay." And so this love for her becomes
hatred,
right?
But this creates an interesting paradox
because it was a similar similar
situation with Dante where Dante loved
Beatatrice but they couldn't be together
and then ultimately Beatric died
and Dante was not like you deserved it
Okay,
sorry. Sorry if am I [laughter] like I
forget we have kids in the room but um
he didn't do that right. He was like,
"No, I still love you, Beatatrice."
Whereas Virgil is like, "Yeah, you
deserved it, man.
What's the difference?" Yes.
>> Um, I just want to ask a question
because I feel like Virgil doesn't
really hate Diddle because like if you
if you look at the line, um, Sakaya's
her husband long ago answers all her
anguish, meets her love with love. So
like basically she's
well she is in the underworld but
she it looks like she gets to live
happily ever after and also like I feel
like there is clear irony towards Ania's
like treachery. So I think and also like
Daido's love for Anias is not like
natural love. is actually like forced
onto her by the gods by Venus and Hera.
So I feel like she is more like the
victim in the Aniad.
>> Yeah. Well, yeah. Um, so everyone agrees
that Ditto is the victim here. Okay. But
if it is true that
she has she's happy where she is, what
she what should she do in when she sees
Inas,
forgive him. Okay. But what should she
do first?
H
>> you should talk to him, respond to him.
>> Okay. How
Yes.
>> Oh, you think I was still brokenhearted
over you? But no, I'm fine.
>> Yeah. I mean, like like she has to do
something, right? Either slap him or
punch him or curse him or just say,
"Haha, I don't care about you anymore."
Okay. But she needs to show him because
of her need for vengeance that I moved
on from you. The fact that she fails to
speak, the fact that she she fails to
respond probably suggests like she's
basically lost her hope. You understand?
Abandon all hope, ye who enter here.
She's lost who she is. And and and
that's what Virgil is saying. Love is
toxic. Okay? And so I would also point
out like Virgil has given her the worst
possible punishment because she's lost
her pride. She's lost her sense of self.
She's become a slave now, right? So, I
think the underlying emotion is Virgil
hates
um Ditto. Um probably because Ditto
thinks he's ugly. Um but again, I mean,
you know, it's a paradox because again,
Dante never consummated it with
Beatatrice,
but he still writes poetry to her and he
elevates her to heaven. And it's the
opposite with Virgil who never
contemplated with Ditto but in response
he casts her to hell. Right. How can we
explain what's going on? Yes.
>> Maybe Dante sees uh Beatric's separation
from him as involuntary while while uh
Virgil thinks that Ditto just kind of uh
refused him voluntarily.
Okay. Yes.
>> The pursuit that Virgil might have
wanted to pursue Ditto or whoever that
person is in real life and just failed
to do so. And so there's this hate,
which is true, but there's also some
nuance love in there cuz he couldn't get
her.
>> No, but but I I understand. I'm saying
that Dante had a similar situation,
right? for Dante's it was again it was
separated but he couldn't do much about
it
>> I guess
>> okay um so we know the story of Dante
and Beatatrice we don't know the story
of Virgil and whoever this ditto is okay
so we're making certain assumptions
right so I'm just saying based on what
we've learned so far how how can we most
simply explain
the the economy
right
let me ask you this question yes One's
love, one's not.
>> Exactly. But but but can explain
>> uh with love is not true. I guess in
Dante's terms, love the the the the love
of God uh is not possessive. It is not
um territorial. It's not vengeful. So,
and uh whatever Virgil had was not love.
>> Okay. So, if you if like Donnie truly
loved Beatatric and Beatric says to you,
Donnie, you're ugly and I met this
really hot guy. What should Donny's
response be?
Oh,
>> like I'm happy for you. Exactly. Right.
Do you understand? That's that's your
only proper response. I'm happy for you
because all I care about is your
happiness. Right. So for Virgil to say
to say, uh, you know what? You betrayed
me. What what what does that tell us
about about Virgil?
He doesn't love this person. Okay. What
does he really want?
control this person. You understand
that's the difference between love and
power. Love is about you giving. Power
is about you taking, right? So the fact
that this person did either uh refused
him or betrayed him made him so angry
that
he turned her into ditto in the uh
Iniad.
Okay. But if you read it, uh, you can't
help but feel tremendous pity for Ditto
and, um, um, okay, does it make sense?
Yes.
>> You, so you're saying you can't help but
feel pity for Ditto and Daido. And so
that's I agree with that. I wonder Daido
is clearly symbolic of Carthage. Anias
is clearly symbolic of Rome. Virgil had
to take these back to Augustus and be
like, "What do you think about my next
chapter of the need?" And he's, it seems
like Augustus is like, "Yeah, great.
Daido's in hell and we want Carthage in
hell."
But just looking at the literary
justice of this, it's easy for a reader
to be like, "Anias is the bad guy here.
He's the liar. He's a manipulator. He's
a jerk. Daido gets unjust punishment
going to hell." So as the reader, we're
siding with the symbolic Carthage. So is
and and so I understand that the Greeks
were famous for like the five act play.
Aristotle wrote poetics.
>> Romans were famous for turning away from
that.
>> And so they might be like, "Haha, we're
the winners here. We're so cool. We're
such great writers."
>> Where Greeks would be like, "You're
you're doing it. You're doing poor
right."
>> Yeah. No, you're absolutely right. If
you were any reader or and you know the
story, you can only feel sympathy for
Ditto, right? And that's why
in the Roman tradition, you were not
allowed to question this. Okay? You had
to believe not only Inas is the hero,
you had to model yourself off him. And
the only way to resolve this paradox,
this contradiction is by simply obeying.
Don't question. Don't think for
yourself, obey. If you think that it is
Ditto who is the hero of the story, and
quite honestly, a lot of people do think
Ditto is the hero of the story, then it
is because Satan has taken you. Okay.
It's because you're being possessed by
Satan,
right? Yes. So you are saying in uh in a
polytheist in an age before Christianity
in an age before this dual dualistic
thinking either you're evil or you're
good uh the Romans were already damning
people to Satan.
>> Okay.
So the Roman culture
believes that the organizing principle
of society is piety. Okay. Obedience.
And the very point of the INIAD is to
model yourself in right. So
yes, intuitively you have problems with
how Inas behaved, but that just shows
you that your intuition is wrong. So
stop thinking yourself and just obey
your teacher, obey your parent, obey the
emperor. Okay? So that's a central
message and this becomes
basically the central organizing
principle for the Catholic Church. Uh
because Paul and Augustine will take
this idea and they will uh systemize it
and make it theological. Okay. Does that
make sense?
>> This is something that makes me curious.
So you said and this passage here with
this paragraph here, it's very clear why
someone might feel uh sympathy for
Ditto. And something I'm wondering about
is that Virgil is not a bad writer. He
knows exactly what he's writing. So if
he's trying to make Ditto the bad guy
here, why did he make her easy to
sympathize with? Why did he not make her
so evil?
>> Yeah, that's a great question. Okay. All
right. So let me explain what's going
on. So the thing about poets is they are
prophets, meaning that whatever comes
from them comes from the divine. Okay?
That's why poetry is beauty and truth
embodied because it's coming it because
the poet is just channeling the divine.
But there are certain cases
where
uh the divine is under the arrest. For
example, you're called before the
emperor of the Roman Empire and you're
told, "Virgil, you're the greatest poet
in the world. I'm gonna give you a
trillion dollars if you write the poem
in the way I I want. And then V's like,
"Sure." And then while he's chanting the
vine,
is like, "The vine is great. This is
great poetry, but it's not what I want,
man. And I'll give you $2 or I'll cut
off your head. Your choice, man." Okay.
And that is why the the INIAD is
structured the way it is. It's it's a
complete mess if you actually read it.
There are a lot of contradictions. Ingus
is in the INIAD because clearly the poet
is not working
uh like just out of his own free will.
He's working under a lot of um under a
lot of duress. In fact,
let let me finish. In fact,
um, Virgil,
his last request before he died was,
"Please burn this manuscript." Because
he knows for a fact he's going to burn
in hell for this. Okay. He knows. He
said to
Ro Augustus, "Uh, [laughter]
please burn this." Okay. Um, yeah. I I
want that $2, but now that I'm going to
die, I I I know I'm going to go to hell.
I I rather you burn this. Okay. Uh yes.
>> Why Why would Caesar want you to pity
Ditto?
>> Um
Caesar the emperor
wants to create a new theology for Rome,
right? So he needs a Bible. In the
Bible, certain themes have to be
explicit, okay? To so that he can force
these ideas onto people
because it's poetry. Because um the poet
is summoning the the divine, a lot of
this divine divine divinity cannot be
fully processed.
Does that make sense? So there are going
to be passages that leak out that create
inconsistencies.
Okay, that and and so like in modern
eyes we see Ditto is sympathetic. We see
that Inias is a jerk. But if you are a
emperor, you have certain expectations
and so you're going to see uh this work
in a certain way that conforms to your
expectations. And if you if you read the
entirety of the Iniad, most of it, 90%
of it, 99% of it is conforming to his
expectations. Okay? He's not smart
enough to actually know about the
leakages because he lacks sympathy. He
lacks empathy. Okay? The thing about
politicians, powerful people, is like
they really lack empathy,
which means that they lack the capacity
to read with nuance and with subtlety.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
Okay. Um, so,
um, so do do you guys understand what's
going on? Okay. All right. So, it is not
Virgil's intention. It is not, uh,
Augusta's intention that we sympathize
with Ditto, but because it's poetry, it
has a life of its own. And so, there are
certain parts uh, that are beyond
control. Okay. All right. So, let's
continue. Divine Comedy. Okay.
>> Countto five, line 67.
C. Paris, Tristan. And he pointed out a
name to me more than a thousand shades
departed from our life because of love.
No sooner had I heard my teacher name
the ancient ladies and the knights, then
pity seized me, and I was like a man
astray. My first words, poet, I should
willingly speak with those two who go
together there and seem so lightly
carried by the wind. and he to me.
You'll see when they draw closer to us,
and then you may appeal to them. By that
love which impels them, they will come.
No sooner had the wind bent them toward
us than I urged on my voice. Oh,
battered souls, if one does not forbid
it, speak with us. Even as doves, when
summoned by desire, born forward by
their will, moved through the air with
wings uplifted still to their sweet
nest, those spirits left the ranks where
ditto suffers, approaching us through
the malignant air so powerful had been
my loving cry.
>> Okay. Stop. Okay. All right. So, um, at
this stage, Dante is a student of
Virgil, and Dante worships Virgil. But
if we if we read the text carefully and
critically, we know
that not all is what it seems. Okay? And
here in these few lines,
Dante
commits an act of rebellion against
Virgil. He commits an act of defiance
against Ditto. H sorry, against Virgil.
What is it?
naming Ditto.
>> Yeah, he names Ditto. Okay, do you
understand? Because remember what
happened was that Virgil would go on
about a thousand different people and he
would name all of them, but he would not
name Ditto because he hates Ditto and
and honestly he's ashamed of what he did
to Ditto, right? And so Dante, what he's
doing is
away from the speech of Virgil, he names
Ditto somewhere else to restore Ditto.
Does that make sense? You see that
nuance here, right? So, it's an act of
rebellion. It's an act of defiance that
foreshadows
uh paradise. Okay. What is to come. All
right. Uh keep on going.
Line 82.
Even as doves, when summoned by desire,
born forward by their will, moved
through the air with wings uplifted
still to their sweet nest, though
spirits left the ranks where ditto
suffers, approaching us through the
malignant air so powerful had been my
loving cry. Verse 88. Oh living being,
gracious and benign, who through the
darkened air have come to visit our
souls that stained the world with blood.
If he who rules the universe were friend
to us, then we should pray to him to
give you peace. for you have pied our
atrocious state. Whatever pleases you to
hear and speak will please us too, to
hear and speak with you now while the
wind is silent in this place. The land
where I was born lies on that shore to
which the poe together with the waters
that follow it descends to final rest.
Love that can quickly seize the gentle
part took hold of him because of the
fair body taken from me. How that was
done still wounds me. Love that releases
no beloved from loving took hold of me
so strongly through his beauty that as
you see it has not left me yet. Love led
the two of us unto one death. Cena waits
for him who took my our love. These
words were born across from them to us.
When I had listened to those injured
souls, I bent my head and held it low
until the poet asked of me, "What are
you thinking?" Okay. So, um, Virgil says
to Dante, "If you really understand
hell, you should talk to these different
souls." Okay. So, Dante talks to these
two souls. These are two people from his
own life in Italy. And they said that,
"Well, you know, we fell in love and
um we went we eloped together, but my
husband found out and he killed us
both." Okay. And um so Virgil asks,
"What do you think of this?" Okay, and
let's let's listen to Dante's response.
>> Line 112. When I replied, my words
began. Alas, how many gentle thoughts,
how deep a longing had led them to the
agonizing pass. Then I dressed my speech
again to them, and I began. Francesca,
your afflictions moved me to tears of
sorrow and of pity. But tell me, in the
time of gentle size, with what and in
what way did love allow you to recognize
you're still in certain longings? And
she, to me, there's no greater sorrow
than thinking back upon a happy time in
misery. And this your teacher knows. Yet
if you long so much to understand the
first fruit of our love, then I shall
tell my tale to you as one who weeps and
speaks. One day to pass the time away,
we read of Lancelot, how love had
overcome him. We were alone and we
suspected nothing. And time and time
again that reading led our eyes to meet
and made our faces pale. And yet one
point alone defeated us. When we had
read how the desired smile was kissed by
one who was so true a lover, this one
who never shall be parted from me, while
all his body trembled, kissed my mouth.
A gal halt indeed. That book and he who
wrote it too. That day we read no more.
And while one spirit said these words to
me, the other wept so that because of
pity I fainted as if I had met my death
and then I fell as a dead body falls.
>> Okay. All right. So the story is that
Franciscaca and her lover. Um at at this
time in history there's something called
courtly love which is like you know just
romantic uh po you write romantic poetry
you declare your love to to someone else
but you don't consummate it. Okay. Um
this is very common uh at this time the
love tradition where you profess your
love but it's not consummated. It's not
sexual at all.
And so Franciscoca and her lover,
they're reading this
poetry, uh, this ro this romance, and
[snorts] then they have the urge to kiss
each other, which pisses off the the,
um, the husband and and they both get
killed.
What is the difference between love and
lust?
Yes. Um speaking from definition, one is
emotion, a thing of a soul and the other
thing is a thing that is physical. But I
think in this context it actually means
uh love is when you wish the best for
someone selfishly and lust is when you
wish to process them.
>> Okay. All right. Anyone else?
So lust also comes from a place of
power, right? Of control,
right? Anyone else?
Yes.
>> Uh so uh love is like a strong emotion
where lust is like impulse I think like
a impulse to to have sex or to to
you know like to follow your feelings.
>> Yes. Okay. So it's impulsive. It's just
something you do on the spirit of the
moment. You do it without reflection.
Okay. Um,
but why is that a sin? Why would that be
a bad thing?
>> Yes.
>> Because you want to control others.
>> Not necessarily. Right. Yes.
>> Uh, because last original thing,
original saying means that it just not a
real thing, just original. It means it
can cause the thing. So maybe lust is
something which can cause this thing can
cause the people to make mistake like
you you you lust someone means you want
to have sex with someone or maybe but
that is desire this desire can let
people to do something badly so like
like a rape or whatever. Yes.
>> Because when you lust for someone that
is an objectification of that person you
objectify them. They are no longer an
individual.
>> Okay. All right. Could you explain some
more?
>> For for example, um
like let's say let's example of
prostitution, right? You um
if you
have lust for let's say a sex worker,
then you are not treating them in a way
that sees them as human but as more like
an object. So it objects it takes away
their sort of the dignity that they they
have as a human.
>> Okay. Okay. So let's carry let's car
this further. Okay. We're trying to
figure out what the difference is
between love and lust. And again it's
not that clear. You know D is completely
confused by this. That's why Donn is f
is faint because he's like what's going
on here? I don't really understand why
lust would necessarily be a sin. Right?
Isn't it possible for you to love
someone and then you love someone?
Right? You first if you see someone
beautiful. Yeah. You're like, you know,
I want her number. I I want to go talk
to her. That's lust. But then you talk
to her. You guys have coffee and you're
like, wow, she's my soulmate. Now you're
in love. So isn't is doesn't lust lead
to love.
What can someone explain to me what's
going on? Yes.
>> Um maybe another part is the lust
focuses on the the outward image while
love is more about like emotional
connection and getting to know them
better.
Yes.
>> Uh I think lust is based on the flesh.
It's based on the body, but uh love is
just based on devotion, based on the
hope or you know inspiration or
something.
>> But but but I'm confused, right? Because
it's just like
h like how do you find love in the first
place?
Right? I mean like
yes. So, if God is love, wouldn't love
be like you're bringing God into the
relationship and then bringing back to
the to the fall. Adam and Eve uh ate the
apple and they saw they were naked and
were shamed. And so, you're hiding from
God. You're in shame. You're bringing
the ego into lust.
>> Yeah. Okay. So, so that that's a really
So, so I'm hearing two really
interesting ideas. Okay. First is that
lust causes you to objectify, which is
to simplify and possess someone. Also,
love is uh is about giving, right? It's
about letting go of your ego, whereas
lust is about fulfilling your ego. Okay?
But I'm still confused as to why lust
would necessarily be a sin.
Why would it be bad?
Right? Because Because like let's
because like let's expand this, okay?
Heaven is where love is. Love means no
fear, right? So if it is a sin, it is
what it's doing is it's causing love to
be degraded. It's causing fear to come
into place. Right? So that's what a sin
is. So why would lust do this? And
again, of all the sins, lust, we're
we're going to descend down to hell. So
lust is like the least light of all the
sins, but it's still a sin. So I'm
confused as to why Franciscaca, you
know, she falls in love and she they
kiss and then she's killed. Why why is
necessarily her fault? Why what's what's
a sin here? Yes. Um, so, uh, before you
mentioned that free will is God's most
precious gift to us. And when you're
lusting over someone, you are violating
your free will. Even if it's in your
mind, like with modern celebrities, some
people say very rude things about them
in comments. And even while that is
legal, it is still a sin because they
are already violating these celebrities
in their minds.
But I mean, I'm trying to figure out why
loving someone and lusting someone, why
loving someone would not violate the
free will, but lusting someone would
violate the free will. Yeah. Yes.
>> Because like lusting someone is more
driven by your like physical drive. And
here like Franciscoca, she went over her
ability to reason. She basically
betrayed her husband and that is sin
sinful because it's misordered. And love
is more like driven by your spiritual
connection. So it goes beyond lust. It's
more of your free will because you
personally resonate with this specific
person. But like lust technically anyone
who's physically attractive can be.
>> So is sex a sin?
>> A target?
>> Is sex a sin?
>> No, but misorder sexes.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. All right. Um
Yeah. Um any any more thoughts be before
we continue?
Okay. So what I'm hearing is um love is
spiritual connection.
Uh lust is physical connection. Uh lust
is the objectification of someone. Um
love is the appreciation of someone and
that person's complexity
uh and contradictions.
And um
um lust is about possession about
controlling someone whereas love is
about giving yourself. Okay. So so there
are lots of differences. Okay. All
right. Let's let let's let's continue
six. Upon my mind's reviving, it had
closed on hearing the lament of those
two kindred. Then sorrow had confounded
me completely. I see new sufferings, new
sufferers surrounding me on every side.
Wherever I move or turn about or set my
eyes, I'm in the third circle filled
with cold, unending, heavy, and a cursed
rain. Its measure and its kind are never
changed. Gross hailstones, water gray
with filth, and snow come streaking down
across the shadowed air. The earth as it
receives that shower stinks. Over the
souls of those submerged beneath that
mess is an outlandish vicious beast. His
three throats barking doglike serverous.
His eyes are blood red, greasy black.
His beard, his belly bulges, and his
hands are claws. His talons tear and fle
and ren the shades. That downpour makes
the sinners howl like door dogs. They
use one of their sides to screen the
other. Those miserable wretches turn and
turn. When Cerberus the great worm
noticed us, he opened wide his mouth,
showed us his fangs. There was no part
of him that did not twitch. My guide
opened his hands to their full span,
plucked up some earth, and with his
fists filled full, he hurled it straight
into those famished jaws. Just as a dog
that barks with greedy hunger would will
then fall quiet when he gnaws his food
intent and straining hard to cram it in.
So were the filthy faces that the demon
Cberus transformed after he'd stunned
the spirits. So they wished that they
were deaf.
>> Okay, so there's Cberus um who's
threatening them and then Virgil
basically feeds them. Okay, so again,
this gives us the idea that Virgil
really is the emperor of hell. He's able
to control the demons here. Okay, keep
on going.
Line 34. We walked across the shades on
whom there thuds that heavy rain and set
our souls upon their empty images that
seem like persons. And all those spirits
lay upon the ground except for one who
sat erect as soon as he caught sight of
us in front of him. Oh you who are
conducted through this hell, he said to
me, recall me if you can, for you before
I was unmade were made. and I to him. It
is perhaps your anguish that snatches
you out of my memory so that it seems
that I have never seen you. But tell me
who you are, you who are set in such a
dismal place, such punishment. If other
pains are more and none more disgusting,
and he to me, your city, one soul of so
full of envy that its sack has always
built, that city held me in the sunlet
life. The name your citizens gave me was
Choco. And for the damning sin of
gluttony, as you can see, I languish in
the rain. And I, a wretched soul, am not
alone. For all of these have the same
penalty for this same sin. And he said
no more. I answered him, "Jo, your
suffering so awaits on me that I'm
forced to weep. But tell me if you know
what end awaits the citizens of that
divided city. Is any just man there?
Tell me the reason why it has been
assailed by so much schism.
And he to me after long controversy
they'll come to blood. The party of the
woods will chase the other out with much
offense. But then within three sons they
too must fail at which the other party
will prevail using the power of one who
taxs his sails. This party will hold it
high his its head for long and heap
great hates great weight upon its
enemies. However much they weep
indignantly, two men are just, but no
one listens to them. Three sparks that
send on fire every heart are envy,
pride, and aiciousness.
With this his words, inciting tears were
done. And I to him, I would learn more
from you. I ask you for a gift of
further speech. To go, for Renata, men
so worthy, Arrigo, Mosca, Yakapo,
Rustikuchi, and all the rest whose minds
bent toward the good. Do tell me where
they are and let me meet them. For my
great longing drives me on to learn if
heaven sweetens or hell poisons them.
And he they are among the blackest
souls. A different scene, a different
sin has dragged them to the bottom. If
you descend so low, there you can see
them. But when you have returned to the
sweet world, I pray recall me to men's
memory. I say no more to you. Answer no
more. Then his straight gaze grew
twisted and ary. He looked at me a while
and bent his heads. He fell as low as
all his blind companions. And my guide
said to me, "He'll rise no more until
the blast of the angelic trumpet upon
the coming of the hostile judge. Each
one shall see his sorry tomb again and
once again take on his flesh and form
and hear what shall resound eternally."
So did we pass across that squalid
mixture of shadows and of rain? Our
steps slowed down, talking a while about
the life to come, at which I said, "And
after the great sentence, oh master,
will these torments grow or else be
less, or will they just be as intense?"
And he to me, remember now your science
which says that when a thing has more
perfection, so much the greater is its
pain or pleasure. Though these oursed
sinners never shall attain the true
perfection, yet they can expect to be
more perfect than than now. We took the
circling way trace by the road. We said
much more than I can hear recount. We
reached the point that marks the
downward slope. Here we found Plutus,
the great enemy.
>> Okay, so certain points about this
passage. First of all, um uh who Dante
is meeting are people he's he knew from
his life in Florence. Okay. So, a lot of
his spoken enemies will be here
condemned in in hell. Um,
the other thing is
um I want to talk about the nature of
these punishments in hell. What are
these punishments trying to do? Why are
they constructed the way it is? Because
uh we were in a circle of lust and so
these people are being whooped around by
the wind. Okay. Now we are in the third
circle which is people are being
punished for gluttony. Right. And what
is the punishment? All the rain. They're
being rained on. Okay. Explain me why
rain would be a fitting punishment for
gluttony.
Uh yes.
>> So there's a lot of factor here. First
of all, there's this saying the fires of
lust. So symbolically the rain is meant
to put out the fires of lust. and not so
symbolically like imagine you are
thirsty because hell is hot and you're
standing in the middle of the rain and
there is no water beneath you. There's
no jug of water and you just have to
open your mouth and let the raindrops
fall into your mouth little by little,
little by little and no matter how much
you want it, no matter how much you uh
wave the rain towards you with your
hands, no more rain will come than what
rain will come. So you can't satisfy
your lust.
Um, okay. Well, it's raining for all
eternity,
right?
Right. Let's visualize this. Okay. What
is gluttony?
>> What is
>> Yes.
>> Gluttony is um the narrow sense is
eating too much food or eating excessive
amounts of food or lavish food. But on a
wider definition, it's uh desiring too
much and like indulging in excessive
pleasures.
>> Yes. Okay. Yeah.
>> Not being able to stop.
>> Yeah. Not stopping. Always desiring.
Just not able to restrain yourself.
Okay. That's what gluttony is.
Um
why why would Yes.
>> How is gluttony different from greed?
That's a great question. Okay. Anyone?
What are you doing with greed? We we
will actually enter the circle of greed,
right? Yes.
>> Greed greed might be personal gain at
the expense of others. But like gluttony
is just not being able to control
yourself.
>> That's right. That's right. Okay. So
greed you are stealing from others
essentially. Does that make sense?
Right. Whereas gluttony is you're just
uh Yes.
>> Could you say that greed is wanting a
lot of things and gluttony is wanting a
lot of the same thing?
>> Um well I mean like if you want money
right you're still greedy right is it's
right. So like but like like the main
issue is greed is you're actually taking
from others. Does that make sense? Yes.
I don't know so much about that. Like to
me it feels like uh greed is when you
take things and gluttony is when you
take things and then you consume them.
So for for example if you see a a person
who is overeating like obviously
overeating and wasting wasting food and
and maybe vomiting it out. You wouldn't
say wow you're so greedy. You would say
you are glutton and
>> yeah but but that's what we're saying.
Gluttony is like you just want too much
whereas greeding you're taking from from
others.
>> No, like like gluttony is when you take
things and you consume them. You reduce
them to nothing. And greed is when you
take things
>> and what and and and you're taking
taking these things from where?
>> Like there's an extra step after
gluttony. That's what I'm trying to put
point out.
>> Okay. All right. All right. So So let's
let's continue. Okay. So gluttony is you
want too much and you can never stop
from wanting too much. So why would
raining on you be the punishment? What's
the logic of this?
>> Make you awake and dull you of your
desire.
Do you of your desire?
Huh?
Yes.
>> Be given to you as a punishment like
endless rain.
>> Yes. Can you explain this?
>> So it's kind of like a tooth for a
tooth. So if you you are gluttonous, you
want more and more and more and never
satisfied you. So raining more and more
and more on you is like the right
punishment for you.
>> But but but why would it be the right
punishment for you? Because I I
understand that as a punishment, right?
But why would that be the right
punishment? because it never satisfy
you.
It's just raining on you. You don't
consume it or do anything with it.
>> Do you think are being enjoy being
rained on?
>> No.
>> Right. So So what's going on here?
>> I think which is why I I mentioned not
being able to stop. It's to me a
gluttonous person is a person that keep
that like you know we all know that you
just keep keep eat. You're just not able
to stop consuming.
>> All right guys again again you have to
use your imagination. Okay. So the the
sin is gluttony. Okay, the sin is
gluttony. And I want to and people who
are gluttonous tend to be fat, right?
Gluttony. Okay,
fat.
All right, so let's just think of
different punishments. Okay, we don't
have to think about the logic or justice
of it, but let's think of like how if we
were designing hell and you, you know,
this person is fat or gluttonous, what
could we do to this person?
Nothing to eat.
>> Okay. Okay. Nothing to eat. Sure. Okay.
Nothingness. Right. You are just in a
prison by yourself. Like solitary
confinement. There's nothing to do.
Okay. That's one possible punishment.
Okay. What else?
>> Feed them to death.
>> Excuse me.
>> Okay. Yeah. Like just too much food.
Okay.
So, like you just balloon out, right?
Just like cake after cake. It's like
it's like Have Have you guys ever seen
the Homer sorry the um Simpsons episode
when Homer's in hell? And then like and
then the devil's like, "Ha, you like
donuts, right?" And so what they do is
they create this machine which feeds
donuts to Homer for all eternity. It's
like, "Oh."
And that was like eventually he's going
to mom it. But Homer's like in ecstasy.
Okay. He's like, "Oh, yes. Yes. Uh,
yes."
>> Um, me.
>> Uh, you then you
>> Okay. Maybe like let them to do some
exercise.
>> Good. Yeah. Treadmill, man. This is
awesome. You're fat. I'll make you
exercise for the rest of your life until
you're thin, right? Uh, yes.
>> Maybe just put food. it out of your
range. You can see it, but you cannot
>> Yeah, that's a really good punishment,
right? Like like you're on a treadmill
and there's a cake in front of you and
you're running around as fast as you
can, but you can never actually touch
the cake. Okay, so yeah. So maybe um
cake out of reach.
Yeah, these are great punishments.
What else? Yes.
>> Um I just have to point something out
like
>> Can you not do this, please?
>> I have to do this because I find this
really upsetting. People are fat for a
lot of reasons other than gluttony. And
I think that reducing fat equals
gluttony. I think it's really reductive
and it's really offensive.
>> This is just this is an exercise. Okay.
>> I think it's really offensive.
>> Okay. All right. You're gluttony. Okay.
So like, oh, you're not fat, but but
you're gluttonous. Okay. All right.
Okay. Um
Okay. I hate to say this, but every day
I teach for four hours, and it's a
really hard to teach for four hours.
Okay. I always have to concentrate
thinking. So if you are interrupting me
or if you're trying to divert my
attention, it causes my brain to be even
more fatigued. Okay. It is exhausting.
Okay. Well, I'm telling you what you
what's happening because this is this is
my my sixth day.
>> Answer all the questions of that lady.
>> Okay. Okay. All right.
>> You can you can ask me questions. Okay.
I'll answer everyone. I promise.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. All right. Let's
let's keep on going. Okay. The cake is
out of reach. You are uh running uh very
very far. Okay. So, these are all great
punishments. Okay.
And what they're doing is punishing. You
understand?
It's punishing you for
your gluttony. And that's what we think
hell is. Hell is about punishment.
Yeah. Go ahead.
>> Um, can I I mean I'm I'm just linking
this to lust and the punishment for
lust.
>> Yes. Which is like being bored around
>> being world around. It's almost like the
consequence of what you cause to others
in the world.
>> Yes. Exactly. Okay. So we think that
hell is a place of punishment.
But for Dante, hell is also a place of
justice, but redemptive justice to force
you into reflection, to force you to
recognize the hurt you've caused others.
Does that make sense? Okay. So, um the
so you are you have gluttony and it's
raining on you and it never stops. Okay.
So what what it's telling you is that is
just an expression of your gluttony.
Okay, a rain that can't stop.
Okay, does that make sense? Okay, that's
why hell is designed the way it is. It's
not designed to punish because if you
want to punish, there are like a million
ways we could punish anyone, right? We
just have to use our imagination. These
are great punishments and we would laugh
at this. But the point of hell is not to
punish. The point of hell is to force
reflection,
to force people to recognize what the
problem is and um what they can do about
it.
Okay. Does that make sense? Okay.
Any questions?
>> All right. Uh yes.
>> Yeah. I mean I uh Yes. hell that that
the the um tornado in for lust and this
one for Buttonly but also in heaven too.
Peicardia is also stuck in a in a loop.
I just noticed the pattern even between
inferno and and and there is symmetry
here. I'm just saying.
>> Yes. Exactly. Okay. Yes. You're exactly
right. Yes.
>> How does being in a tornado um help you
reflect?
>> No. No. It's it's trying to manifest
visualize for you the problem with lust.
And the idea is that you are inconstant.
Okay. You're always changing your mind.
Okay. That's a problem with lust. Like
if you see something beautiful, you want
it. But then you see something more
beautiful, you want that. Okay. Uh yes.
>> Um we have a very interesting comment
from the live stream. Okay. And uh one
person mentioned that uh she thinks that
uh the punishment is quite similar. We
can take the um Japanese animation film
Spirited Away. Okay.
>> As an example, because she thinks the
pigs in the film is quite similar to
this punishment and um she
greed is like something saying like I
want more and gluttony is like I can't
stop. It's just like the pigs in the
film.
>> Good. Yeah. Exactly. Right. So greed is
like I want I want more. I want I want
from others. Glenn, I can't stop. Okay,
good. Okay. All right. But does that
make sense to you? Okay. Hell is
constructed not as a place to make you
afraid
to punish you. It's hell is a place
constructed to force you into
seeing for yourself
the problems and dangers of your sin.
Okay. Does that make sense? Okay. All
right. Uh yes.
consequence and the principle behind
your sin to make you realize the sin's
essence and what it does to you or your
body or the others around you.
>> Yes. Okay. Right. So again, it it's to
put a mirror to your face. Okay. All
right. Let's keep on reading.
Kanto 7
P Satan pap Satan alle so Plutus with
his grading voice began the gentle sage
aware of everything said reassuringly
don't let your fear defeat you for
whatever power he has he cannot stop our
climbing down this crag then he turned
back to Plutus's swollen face and said
to him be quiet cursed wolf let your
vindictiveness feed on yourself he's no
his is no random journey to the deep it
has been willed on high where Michael
took revenge upon the arrogant
rebellion. As sails inflated by the wind
collapsed and tangled in a heap when the
mass cracks so that ferocious beast fell
to the ground. Thus we made our way down
to the fourth ditch to take in more of
that despondent shore where all the
universe's ill is stored. Justice of God
who has amassed as many strange tortures
and travails as I have seen. Why do we
let our guilt consume us so? Even as
waves that break above Kuribdis, each
shattering the other when they meet, so
must the spirits here dance their round
dance here more than else where I saw
multitudes to every side of me. Their
howls were loud while wheeling weights.
They used their chests to push. They
struck against each other at that point.
Each turned around and wheeling back
those weights, cried out, "Why do you
hoard? Why do you squander? So did they
move around the sorry circle from left
and right to the opposing point. Again,
again they cried their chant of scorn.
And so when each of them had changed
positions, he circled halfway back to
his next joust. And I who felt my heart
almost pierced through requested,
"Master, show me now what shades are
these, and tell me if they all were
clerics, those conjured ones who circle
on our left. And he to me, "All these
two, left and right, were so squint eyed
of mind in the first life, no spending
that they did was done with measure."
Their voices spark this out with clarity
when they have reached the two points of
the circle where their opposing guilts
divide their ranks. These to the left,
their heads bereft of hair were
clergymen and popes and cardinals with
him whom avarest works its excess. And I
to him, master among this kind, I
certainly might hope to recognize some
who have been bespattered by these
crimes. And he to me, that thought of
yours is empty, that the undescerning
life that made them filthy now renders
them unrecognizable.
For all eternity they'll come to blows.
These here will rise up from their
seulers with fists clenched tight, and
these with haircropped close, ill-giving
and illing, have robbed both of the fair
world, and set them to this frockus.
What that is like my words need not
embellish. Now you can see, my son, how
brief the sport of all those goods that
are in fortune's care,
for which the tribe of men contend and
brawl, for all the gold that is wherever
was beneath the moon could never offer
rest to even one of these exhausted
spirits.
Master, I asked of him, now tell me too,
this fortune whom you've touched upon
just now, what she who clutches so all
the world's goods. And he to me, "Oh
unenlightened creatures, how deep the
ignorance that hampers you. I want you
to digest my word on this. Who made the
heavens? Who gave them guide? Was he
whose wisdom transcends everything that
every part may shine unto the other? He
had the light aortioned equally
similarly for worldly splenders. He
ordained a general minister and guide to
shift. From time to time those empty
goods from nation unto nation, clan to
clan in ways that human reason can't
prevent. Just so when people rules, one
languishes, obeying the decision she has
given, which like a serpent in the grass
is hidden. Your knowledge cannot stand
against her force. For she foresees and
judges and maintains her kingdom as the
other gods do theirs.
The changes that she brings are without
resppite. It is necess it is necessity
that makes her ship swift. And for this
reason, men change state so often.
She's the one so frequently maligned
even by those who should give praise to
her. They blame her wrongfully with
words of scorn. But she's blessed and do
not hear these things. For with the
other primal beings happy, she turns her
sphere and glories in her bliss. But now
let us descend to greater sorrow. For
every star that rose when I first moved
is setting now we cannot stay too long.
We crossed the circle to the other
shore. We reached a foaming water course
that spills into a trench formed by its
overflow. That stream was even darker
than deep purple and we together with
those shadowed waves moved downward and
along a strange pathway. When it was
reached, when it has reached the foot of
those malign gray floats, that
melancholy stream descends, forming a
swamp that bears the name of sticks. And
I who was intent on watching it could
make out muddied people in that slime,
all naked, and their faces furious.
These struck each other not with hands
alone, but with their heads and chest,
and with their feet, and tore each other
peacemeal with their teeth. The kindly
master told me, "Son, now see the souls
of those whom Ganganger has defeated,
and I should also have you know for
certain that underneath the water there
are souls who sigh and make this plane
of water bubble. As your eye, looking
anywhere can tell, wedged in the slime,
they say we had been sullen in the sweet
air that's gladdened by the sun. We bore
the mist of sluggishness in us. Now
we're bitter in the blackened mud. This
hymn they have to gurgle in their
gullets because they cannot speak it in
full words. And so between the dry shore
and the swamp, we circled much of that
disgusting pond. Our eyes upon the
swallowers of slime. We came at last
upon a tower's base.
>> Okay, so we are um going down in these
circles. We encounter people who are
greedy. What is the punishment?
>> They have to push rocks around.
Okay.
>> In a circle.
>> In a circle. Uh, what else?
Okay.
What else?
And why would this be a fitting
punishment for them? Again, it's really
important for us to appreciate the point
of these punishments is not to punish
but to force reflection.
Okay? To force you to recognize the
error of your ways so that you can
choose
to make uh a better decision. Okay? This
is this is about redemptive justice as
opposed to just pure vengeance.
What is the logic of this punishment?
>> Uh, yes.
>> Art for nothing because you're pushing
these rocks around in circles and it's
just that you're greedy. You get a lot
of these earthly things and at the end
you it comes down to nothing. You put so
much work.
>> Exactly. Yeah. Yeah. That's very
beautiful. Thank you. Yes.
>> Maybe try to let people redeem redeem
and try to be uh salvation or something.
>> Yes. Okay. Right. Exactly. Okay. Yes.
Anyone else?
Okay. All right. The anger. What's the
punishment for the for the anger?
>> They have to wrestle each other in mud.
>> Okay. And And what else?
And they're submerged underwater.
>> Yes. And And what else?
>> The swallow swallow swine. And they're
also like Aren't they also cannibalizing
each other? Aren't they also eating each
other? So So, so what's the why is this
a fitting punishment?
of forgiveness or
>> yeah for forgiveness it means to forgive
people.
>> Yes.
>> When you are angry you kind of bite off
each other like you're mad at each
other. You have you want to tore each
other apart but you're also like kind of
drowning in your own anger that you are
swallowing basically because it's
killing your body. That's how you a lot
of people get cancer and all kinds of
disease when you're angry.
>> Exactly. Okay. So you think you are
hurting others but you're actually
hurting yourself. You're consuming
others, but you're also consuming
yourself in the process. Okay. All
right. Yes.
>> I wonder what is um the river sts doing
here.
>> Excuse me.
>> Um why why are they drowned in the river
st?
>> Okay. All right. So when you read the
divine comedy, each of these different
realms, whether they are uh infernal,
purgatory or paradise, there's always a
complex geography to these realms and
there are certain demarcation points
which um suggest we are entering a new
level. Okay, do you understand? So the
sins that we've encountered so far,
whether they be lust,
um, gluttony, greed, anger,
they're bad, but they're not that bad.
Okay, when we cross river stakes, when
we enter uh new territory, this is like
even worse sins.
Okay. Um, so these are things that may
make others uncomfortable. They make
they make make your life terrible, but
they're not actually disrupting the
fundamental structure of the universe.
Whereas you go lower and lower, these
people are in fact um destroying the
very fabric of the universe. Okay, does
that make sense? Okay. So, so what Donna
is trying to do is trying to separate
these different regions of hell as well.
Okay. All right. Okay. Any more
questions before we move on?
All right. Let's let's let's keep on
going. Okay.
KTO 8.
I say, continuing that long before we
too had reached the foot of that tall
tower, our eyes had risen upward towards
its summit, because of two small flames
that flickered there, while still
another flame returned their signal so
far off it was scarcely visible. And I
turned toward the sea of all good sense,
I said, "What does this mean? And what
reply comes from that other fire? Who
kindled it?" And he to me, "Above the
filthy waters, you can already see what
waits for us. If it's not hid by vapors
from the marsh, bow string has not
thrust from itself an arrow that ever
rushed as swiftly through the air as did
the little bark that at that moment I
saw as it skimmed toward us on the water
a solitary boatman at its helm. I heard
him howl. Now you're caught, foul soul.
Oh, flegus flegus. Such a shout is
useless this time, my master said. where
yours no longer than it will take to
cross the muddy slle. And just as one
who hears some great deception was done
to him and then resents it, so was so
was fleg when he had to store his anger.
My guide preceded me into the boat once
he was in. He had me follow him. There
seemed to be no wait until I boarded. No
sooner were my guide and I embarked than
off that ancient prow went cutting water
more deeply than it does when bearing
others. And while we steered across the
stagnant channel before me stood a
sinner thick with mud, saying, "Who are
you? Come before your time." And I to
him I've come, but I don't stay. But who
are you have become so ugly? He
answered, "You can see I'm one who
heaps, who weeps, and I to him. In
weeping and in grieving a cursed spirit,
may you long remain. Though you're
disguised by filth, I know your name."
Then he stretched both his hands out
toward the boat at which my master
quickly shoved him back, saying, "Be off
there with the other dogs." That done,
he threw his arms around my neck and
kissed my face and said, "In indignant
soul, blessed is she who bore you in her
womb." When in the world he was
presumptuous, there's no good to guilt
his memory. And so his shade down here
is hot with fury. How many up above now
count themselves great kings who wall
here like pigs in slime, leaving behind
foul memories of their crimes?
And I, oh master, I'm very eager to see
that spirit sousted within this broth
before we've made our way across the
lake. And he to me, before the other
shore comes into view, you shall be
satisfied to gratify so fine a wish is
right. Soon after I heard I had heard
these words, I saw the muddy sinner so
dismember him that even now I praise and
thank God for it. They were all
shouting. They all were shouting at
Filippo Argenti. At this the Florentine
gone wild with spleen began to turn his
teeth against himself. We left him
there. I told no more of him, but in my
near but in my ear so loud a wailing
pounded that I leaned forward all intent
to see.
The kindly master said, "My son, the
city that bears the name of D is drawn
near with its grave citizens, its great
battalions." I said, "I can already see
distinctly, master, the mosques that
gleam within the valley as crimson, as
if they had just been drawn out of the
fire."
He told me, "The eternal flame burning
there appears to make me make them red,
as you can see within this lower hell."
So we arrived inside the deep cut
trenches that are the moes of this
despondent land. The ramparts seem to me
to be of iron. But not before we'd
ranged in a wide circuit did we approach
a place where there that shrill pilot
shouted, "Get out! The entrance way is
here." Above the gates, I saw more than
a thousand who once had reigned from
heaven, and they cried in anger, "Who is
this who without death can journey
through the kingdom of the dead?" And my
wise master made a sign that said he
wanted to speak secretly to them. Then
they suppressed somewhat their great
disdain and said, "You come alone. Let
him be gone, for he was reckless
entering this realm. Let him return
alone on his mad road. Or try to if that
he can, since you, his guide, across so
dark a land, you are to stay."
Consider, reader, my dismay before the
sound of those abominable words.
Returning here seemed so impossible.
Oh my dear God, who more than seven
times has given back to me my confidence
and snatched me from deep danger that
had menaced. Do not disturb me when I'm
so undone. And if they will not let us
pass beyond, let us retrace our steps
together quickly. These were my words,
the Lord who led me there replied,
"Forget your fear. No one can hinder our
passage. One so great has granted it.
But you wait here for me and feed and
comfort your tired spirit with good
hope. For I will not abandon you in this
low world.
And so he goes on his way. That gentle
father has left me there to wait and
hesitate. For yes and no contend within
my head. I could not hear what he was
telling them, but he had not been long
with them when each ran back into the
city, scrambling fast. And these are
adversaries slammed the gates in my
lord's face, and he remained outside.
Then with slow steps turned back again
to me. His eyes turned to the ground,
his brows deprived of every confidence,
he said with size. See who has kept me
from the house of sorrow. To him he
added, to me he added, you though I am
vexed must not be daunted. I shall win
this contest. Whoever tries within to
block our way. This insolence of theirs
is nothing new. They used it once before
and at a gateless secret. It is still
without its bolt. the place where you
made out the fatal text and now already
within that gate and across the circles
and alone descends the one who will
unlock this realm for us.
>> Okay, so um for the past few kantos
we've established that Virgil is the
master of hell. He's able to navigate it
pretty easily. These demons obey him.
They do whatever he tells them. He
understands the geography of hell very
intimately. Now we cross the river
sticks and we enter, we are about to
enter the city of this. Okay, the this
is the home of the fallen angels. Those
who rebelled against God and now they
are um in hell. This is is where is
where they live. Within this we will
find Lucifer or Satan.
What's going on here? He's trying to get
into the city and the demons say screw
off. Uh this guy Dante doesn't belong
here. We'll let you in, Virgil, but we
won't let in Dante. And Virgil says,
"Let us talk in private." So they talk
privately and then they're like, "No,
he's he's not coming in." Okay.
Why do we have this scene? What is Dante
trying to convey or trying to
um
say about the nature of hell
or anything? Any thoughts, any comments
about what's going on?
Yes.
on terms with the devil and they are
like good buddies almost like there's a
brotherhood there.
>> Yeah. So, so what the devils are saying
is that you've been here before. Uh we
know you but we're still at Maggalene
and Dante.
>> Yes.
>> Um Virgil is the master of outer hell
not inner hell.
>> Okay.
>> Because he stops at the this right. So
he's he's even he doesn't have authority
to say who goes in and out of the court.
>> Okay. What else?
Yes.
>> Um my question I have a question is why
do the angels call Dante a madman or
reckless for entering the realm of the
dead without dying? Like why do they
call him a mad man?
>> Well well would you want to go into
hell?
>> No.
>> Yeah. Well it's like what are you doing
here man? You're still alive and you
choose to walk among us. Are you crazy?
Okay. That that that's what they're
saying.
Yes.
>> Love that he has sent Beatatric to
heaven. So, he's someone with love, so
he shouldn't be where the demons are and
he still has reverence for God, I guess,
a little bit. Um, so the demons think
that he doesn't belong there. Like,
what?
>> Well, they told him he doesn't belong
there because it's a body. He's still
alive, right? They don't really know
about Beatatric. They don't really know
about God. They don't care, right? So,
what's what's going on here?
Anyone else?
>> They're saying that Virgil and Dante are
different. So, Virgil can go into this
place, but Dante can't.
>> Good. Okay. Yeah. So, so it's clearly
there's the difference between Virgil
and Dante. Okay. Ver Donnie is a
stranger to this world. Virgil is very
familiar to this world. Okay. Virgil
belongs here. Okay. So that's implanting
an idea in in in in the uh reader like
like Virgil really belongs here. He's
very intimate here. He's he's probably
very happy here. Yes. And this helps
helps us explain why ultimately he
chooses not to go to heaven. Right. When
when Don takes D to purgatory, the very
top of purgatory, he has opportunity to
ascend to heaven. He chooses not to go.
He just he just rather to just go back
home to limbo.
What else?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. I as a question why why Danty just
has to go to hell? I mean it's just
Virgil who just lead him to to the hell
or D want him he want
>> he is in hell because there's no other
path to heaven, right? He tried these
other paths but they're blocked by these
beast. So So Virgil is like well we
could try to fight these bees but we
probably won't win. So let's just go
another way. Let's just go into hell and
then we'll ascend to heaven through that
way. Okay. So this is the only path to
heaven.
Okay. Um what is the nature of
people in hell?
Why what does sin do to people? And what
why and why would that so why is in
that? Yeah.
>> The people in hell like to control So,
so what do they do always?
>> They boss people around.
>> And so what happens?
>> They gatekeep.
>> They gatekeep. And what happens? They
fight amongst themselves. Do you
understand? Okay. So this is this is a
metaphor for what is happening in Italy
right now? Why are there so many these
different factions in Italy fighting
each other? Why can't they get along?
Right? They know each other. They're
probably born in the same family, but
they're always fighting with each other.
And it's the ego driven by sin, right?
By their gluttony, by their lust, by
their greed, by their anger. That's the
issue in hell. And therefore, there can
be no smooth path in hell. There can be
no unity in hell. They just have to
fight each other all the time. Okay? So,
what's the only way for
Virgil and Dante to get out of this?
Those demons won't let them in.
That's the nature of hell. People don't
get along. They fight all the time. They
they geek. They geek. They are very
territorial.
>> I think Virgil will fight his way in.
>> Good luck, Virgil. You're fighting an
army of demons. Yeah.
>> Bribe them.
>> H
>> bribe.
>> Um what what do you think the first
thing that Virgil tried to do was?
Probably bribe them, right? They had a
private conversation. You can imagine
all the things that that Virgil tried to
tell them, right? like bribing and all
that didn't work.
So,
is there any solution?
>> Yes.
>> Uh Dante and Virgil would need to argue
with each other and maybe fight to show
they're a part of this hell thing.
>> That's interesting. That but that's not
how these things work because again,
these people are geeky. They're they're
territorial, right?
So
they're like, "We don't care. Donna
doesn't belong here. We can access,
right? So what's the only path forward
now?"
Are they able to resolve this conflict
by themselves?
No. Okay. So God has to intervene now,
right? Okay. All right. Let's keep keep
on going.
Kanto 9.
The color cowardice displayed in me when
I saw that my guide was driven back made
him more quickly mask his own new power.
>> So he's very disappointed. He was not
able to convince the demons. Okay, keep
on going.
>> He stood alert like an attentive
listener because his eyes could hardly
journey far across the black air and the
heavy fog. We have to win this battle,
he beca he began. if not but one so
great had off offered help. How slow
that someone's coming to see me. But I
saw well enough how he had covered his
first words with the words that followed
after so different from what he had said
before. Nevertheless, his speech made me
afraid because I drew out from his
broken phrase a meaning worse perhaps
than he'd intended. Does anyone from the
first circle, one whose only punishment
is crippled hope, ever descend so deep
in this sad hollow? That was my
question. and he answered, "So it is
quite rare for one of us to go along the
way that I have taken now, but I in
truth have been here once before." That
savage witch, Erictho, he who she who
called the shades back to their body,
summoned me. My flesh had not been long
stripped off when she had me descend
through all the rings of hell to draw a
spirit back from Judas's circle. That is
the deepest and the darkest place, the
farthest from the heaven that girds all.
So rest assured, I know the pathway
well. The swamp that breeds and breathes
the giant stench surrounds the city of
the sorrowing which now we cannot enter
without anger. And he said more, but I
cannot remember because my eyes had
wholly taken me to that high tower with
the glowing summit where at one single
point there suddenly stood three
infernal furies fleck with blood who had
the limbs of women and their ways. but
wore as girdles snakes of deepest green,
small serpents and horned vipers formed
their hairs, and these were used to bind
their beastial temples.
And he who knew these handmmaids well
they served the queen of never- ending
lamentation
said, "Look at the ferocious Arinis,
that is Mera on the left, and he who
weeps upon the right, that is Alto
between them. He was done. Each fury
tore her breast with talent nails, each
with her palms, beat on herself, and
wailed so loud that I in fear drew near
the poet. Just let Medusa come. Then we
shall turn him into stone. They all
cried, looking down. We should have
punished Thissus's assault. Turn round
and keep your eyes shut fast. For should
the Gorgon show herself and you behold
her, never again would you return above,
my master said. And he himself turned me
around and not content with just my
hands, used his as well to cover up my
eyes. Oh, you possessed of sturdy
intellects observed the teaching that is
hidden here beneath the veiled verses so
obscure. And now across the turbid waves
their past are whereboantic frockets
poured sound enough to make both of the
shorelines quake. A sound no other not
other than a winds when wild because it
must contend with warmer currents. It
strikes against the forest without let
shattering, beating down, bearing off
branches as moves proudly clouds of dust
before it and puts to flight both
animals and shepherds. He freed my eyes
and said, "Now let your optic nerve turn
directly toward that ancient foam there,
where the mist is thickest and most
accurate." As frogs confronted by their
enemy, the snake will scatter underwater
till each hunches in a heap along the
bottom. So did the thousand ruined souls
I saw take flight before a figure
crossing sticks who walked as if on land
and with dry soul. He thrust away the
thick air from his face, waving his left
hand frequently before him. That seemed
the only task that wearied him.
I knew well he was heaven's messenger
and I turned around my master and he
made a sign that I be still and bow
before him. How full of high disdain he
seemed to me. He came up to the gate and
with a wand he opened it for there was
no resistance.
Oh you cast out of heaven hated crowd
were his first words upon that horrid
threshold. Why do you harbor this
presumptuousness?
Why are you so reluctant to endure that
will whose aim can never be cut short
and which so often add into your hurts?
What good is it to thrust against the
fates your server, if you remember well,
for that had both his throat and chin
stripped clean.
At that he turned and took the filthy
road and did not speak to us, but had
the look of one who is obsessed by other
cares. than those that press and not
those before him. And we moved forward
onto on into the city in safety, having
heard his holy words. We made our way
inside without a struggle. And I who
wanted so much to observe the state of
things that such a fortress guarded. As
soon as I had entered, looked about, I
saw on every side a spreading plane of a
lamentation and atrocious pain.
Just as at Arl where Rome becomes a
marsh, just as at Pola near Cornero's
Gulf that closest Italy and bathes its
borders, the seokulers make all the
plain uneven. So they did here on every
side, except that here the seokulers
were much more harsh.
For flames were scattered through the
tombs, and these had kindled all of them
to glowing heat. No artisan could ask
for hotter iron. The lid of every tomb
was lifted up, and from each tomb such
sorry cries arose as could come only
from the sad and hurt. And I, master,
who can these people be buried in great
chests of stone like these must speak by
way of size and agony? And he to me,
here are our heretics and those who
followed them from every sect. Those
tombs are much more crowded than you
think. here like like has been and
supposed with like some monuments are
heated more some less and then he turned
around and to his right we passed
between the torments and high wall.
>> Okay. So um Virgil and Donnie cannot
pass into this and in fact there are
furies and Medusa who threatened them.
Okay. So what saves them is the arrival
of an angel who forces
um this to be opened and the demons
flee.
How does Virgil feel about this?
How does he feel?
You're in trouble. You can't solve a
problem. God sends an angel to help you.
How how would you feel?
>> Embarrassed.
When angel comes and saves you, you feel
embarrassed.
>> Um, well, so, uh, Virgil is supposed to
be really know his way around hell.
>> Yes.
>> And be buds with everyone and have
control, but here it's something that he
can't do. So, it's kind of embarrassing
that he couldn't do that completely on
his own.
>> And so, he's embarrassed, right? So,
what does this tell us about Virgil?
He has a ego.
>> Yeah. He's very proud. Does that make
sense? Because like if any of us were in
trouble, right, and we pray to God,
please come save us. An angel comes and
saves us, we'd be eternally grateful,
right? We'd be like, "Oh, wow. I will
now dedicate myself to loving God for
the rest of my life, and I will spread
this message." And and Virgil is like,
"And what and and what does Virgil say
when the angel arrives?
What does he say and do?
What does he say? Do
Angel came and saved you. What's the
least you can say?
>> Thank you.
>> How about thank you, man? Does Virgil do
this? He does. He doesn't do anything.
didn't see anything. Okay? Meaning he's
tell and this is telling us he's not
actually happy about any of this.
>> Right? Does that make sense?
He's not happy about this. Yeah, the
problem is solved. He couldn't get
through the gates of this and angel came
to help him out, but he's not happy
about any of this because Virgil is
first and foremost obsessed with
control,
his ego, his pride, right? He wants to
be the top dog. He wants to be one in
charge. He wants to be the hero.
And so this is very embarrassing for
um Virgil.
Okay. So he's putting his own feelings
before the larger mission of getting
Dante to heaven.
Right? Because if if you are really
focused on the mission and there's an
angel who opens the gates, what what
what should you say to this angel?
And
if you were really focused on the
mission, if you really wanted Dante to
ascend to heaven and an angel has come
and saved you, what would you say to
him? You would say thank you first of
all and like what else?
>> Help.
>> Yeah, man. Hey, hey, you're going to
heaven, right? Hey, take that with you,
right? Like, seriously, you came all the
way from heaven. You have to go back.
just take that to review.
Problem solved. I completed my mission.
Does that make sense? The fact that he
doesn't say thank you, the fact that he
he doesn't even ask the angel for more
help suggests that Virgil first and
foremost cares about his ego,
right? He wants to be he wants to be the
one to take Dante throughout hell.
Has he has Dante How well does Virgil
know hell?
How well does Virgil know hell?
>> Very well.
>> Like how well
has he been everywhere in hell? Has he
been into the deepest darkest areas of
hell? Yes. Even to Satan. Do you
understand? Okay. So he knows hell very
very well.
Okay. So he knows how to
traverse hell and he himself has said
that he's been to uh every part of hell
even even the deepest darkest circle of
hell. All right.
So again this is making us wonder who
Virgil is what his motivations are
and what he he ultimately has planned
for Dante.
Okay.
Any any questions? Okay. So, um
um we are now at the halfway point of
our seminar. Okay. So, this is um day
six. We start day seven uh tomorrow. Um
we we we will need to go a bit faster.
So, for homework again,
please reread what we've read, okay? So,
you understand what's going on. But also
like there are lots of like good short
videos
on YouTube that introduce inferno
because it's it's a it's a very simple
section as compared with paradise. Okay,
paradise is hard that that's why we had
sp spend a lot of time in paradise but
inferno it's actually pretty simple.
Okay. So make sure like you um do learn
about uh inferno. Okay. Yes.
>> There are reason why I do feel going
from paradise to inferno. Inferno is
much more I wouldn't call it
approachable but it's easier to kind of
go through and kind of follow the story
as opposed to the concepts that you have
to grasp in paradise.
>> Yes.
>> Right.
>> Like literature-wise is there like a it
intended that way?
>> I I think it is because remember um what
what Donnie will do is first publish the
infernal. Okay. And at this time in
history Donnie is not a well-known
person. He's not a very powerful person,
right? So, he wants to make sure that
first of all, whatever he writes is
appealing,
right? That people will want to um read
it and buy the manuscript, but also he's
trying to
um establish himself in a larger poetic
tradition, right? And that means using
famous people like Virgil, right? So
like if if if if it's like Dante in
hell, like who cares, right? But it's
like Virgil taking Dante in hell, that's
an actually interesting cell to people.
Okay. So so so so for him it's like, you
know, how does he get people interested
in the story he's trying to convey? And
that's why, as you point out, the story
in Inferno, it's much more interesting.
It's much more visual than paradise.
Okay. But ultimately he wants us he
wants to take us all to paradise. And to
do that you first need to uh establish a
really compelling story. Okay. With
really famous people. Okay. So uh and
and honestly this is why uh in
universities it's mainly inferno that's
taught and not paradise. Okay. Because
paradise it's actually much more it's
really philosophy as opposed to
literature. Whereas inferno it's very
literary. Okay. It's a great story, lots
of interesting characters, it's very
visual, it's very funny, it's very
interesting. Okay. So, thank you for
that. But, but again, we're trying we're
trying to really understand uh Dante's
Cosmology. Okay. Yes.
>> Um Dante's Inferno reminds me a lot of
uh the Chinese uh novel Journey to the
West.
>> Okay.
>> In the way that it's first of all,
they're both a journey. Second of all,
they both meet monsters and demons and
angels and myth mythic creatures. And
third of all, they have a very big
impact on the society and the culture
and they're both really old. Um
>> yeah,
>> like for example, the way that Journey
to the West is interesting to read
because, you know, they're fighting
demons and uh they're going on a
journey. It's in the in a similar way,
Inferno is interesting to read because,
you know, there's this master, he's
bringing this other person on a journey
and they're trying to get to a
destination.
>> Yeah. No, you're absolutely right in
that uh Inferno, it there's much more of
a narrative angle to it, right? Whereas
in Paradise, it's basically just
philosophy. Uh yes.
>> Yeah. But there's a very big difference
is uh the monster in the western
journey, uh they are all being protected
by by the god by by the you know, some
goddess. But uh in the you know uh
inferno we can see that it's impossible
right because demons or angel they are
quite different world they they can't
just taking control over each other but
I think maybe that is quite quite
different. Yeah.
>> Okay. All right. All right. Any other
more questions or or comments? Okay. All
right. So to summarize um we need to go
very fast for the last um half of this
seminar. Um and so you will have to do a
lot more work. Okay. So re I'll review
what we learned so far and uh on YouTube
there are lots of tutorials, lots of
like good intro videos that introduce to
you uh inferno. Okay. As well as so so
let's um yeah so just make sure you you
understand and and prepare and this will
allow for much richer discussion. Okay.
And again, Inferno is not that hard to
understand as compared with Paradise.
And and that's why I hope that you're
more able to to contribute individually
to it. So the the game plan for the last
half of this uh seminar is for us to
imagine that each and every one of us
will leave the seminar and we will teach
it to someone else. Okay? It could it
could be it could be your students
because you're teachers, but it could
also be your friend. It could also be
your child. It it could also be your
mother. Okay? And it doesn't matter.
Okay? But imagine yourself after you
leave the seminar teaching it to someone
that you love. And what I'm going to do
is rather focus too much on the literary
meaning of the text because um we've
done paradise which is the hardest and
so everything else that follows should
be pretty simple. What I want to focus
more on is giving you the tools to
expand your imagination. as well as to
teach others. Okay, that's why I wanted
to do compare contrast today. Compare
contrast is one of the most effective
tools that you can use so that we can
just say okay well to understand why
rain is such an interesting punishment.
Let's think of other punishments, right?
Okay. So, I'll be doing more of these um
pedagogical techniques as we go uh
along. Okay. But for me to do that, we
have to stay focused on the task at
hand. Okay? And so come in with a spirit
like I'm not here to debate you. I'm not
here to argue you. I'm here to learn how
to teach this to others. Okay? So that's
the last half of our seminar. Okay? We
are we clear? We we've done the hardest
part. We've done paradise. We now know
exactly what this poem is trying to do.
We have a good conception. Now our goal
is to teach it to others. All right.
Okay.